<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vengeance of the temple: discovered in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Major and court of aldermen of the City of London, in Pauls Church, May 17. 1648. Being the day of publique thanksgiving for a victory obtayned by the forces under the command of Colonell Horton, at St. Faggons, neere Cardiffe in Wales. / By William Strong pastor of Dunstans in the west, and a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E450_20</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863877</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161909</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161909)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E450[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vengeance of the temple: discovered in a sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Major and court of aldermen of the City of London, in Pauls Church, May 17. 1648. Being the day of publique thanksgiving for a victory obtayned by the forces under the command of Colonell Horton, at St. Faggons, neere Cardiffe in Wales. / By William Strong pastor of Dunstans in the west, and a member of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 49, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Benson, and are to be sold at his shop in Dunstans Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached in Paules Church before the Lord Mayor and aldermen.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Horton, Thomas, d. 1673 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161909:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Vengeance of the Temple:</hi> DISCOVERED IN A SERMON Preached before the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen of the City of London, in Pauls Church, <hi>May</hi> 17. 1648.</p>
            <p>Being the day of Publique Thankſgiving for a Victory obtayned by the Forces under the Command of Colonell <hi>Horton,</hi> at St. <hi>Faggons,</hi> neere <hi>Cardiffe</hi> in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Strong</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Dunſtans</hi> in the Weſt, and a Member of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Benſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:161909:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:161909:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable the Lord Major and Court of Aldermen, of the famous City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, and Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Word ſpoken in ſeaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is a word upon the wheeles <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us. <hi>Prov. 25.11.</hi> both <hi>grateful</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſefull,</hi> which is the bleſsing that I begge of God upon theſe poore and meane endeavours, which in obedience to your command I humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you.</p>
            <p>It was the fitteſt ſubject that in this juncture of time I could fix my thoughts upon, when mens hearts are too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally turned to hate Gods people, and to deale deceitfully with his ſervants; therby (I feare) to prepare inſtruments in judgement for that laſt act of the tragedy upon the Saints in the Reformed Churches, the killing of the witneſſes, which I conceive, as the bittereſt affliction, and the ſharpeſt perſecution is yet to come.</p>
            <p>God hath put great opportunity into your bands, and it may be hath raiſed you to honour for ſuch a time as this: do you countenance, and act for the Lords holy ones, and it ſhall be accepted as a ſervice by him who is King of Saints: doe you become as a correcting Cherube unto this Arke of God among you: for next to the honourable title of <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Faith,</hi> is that of <hi>Protector of the faithfull:</hi> for God and his people are engaged in the ſame cauſe and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel and all oppoſition ſhall end in the deſtruction of the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,
<pb facs="tcp:161909:3"/>and they ſhall periſh by their hands whom they oppoſe, even by <hi>the vengeance of the Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But no man will ever be faithfull to the Saints, but hee that is himſelfe a Saint, in whom the ſpirit of God dwels as a man, and acts as a Magiſtrate; all other men though they may give good words for a time, yet they will meet with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an opportunity of temptation, and they will fall off,
<note place="margin">Pelago ſe non ita commiſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus eſſet, quin quando libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, pedem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre poſſet.</note> engaging themſelves in the cauſe of the Saints no further, then may ſtand with their preſent purpoſes, and deſignes: As the King of <hi>Navarre</hi> told. <hi>Bez.</hi> he would lanch no further into the Proteſtant cauſe, then he might ſee which way to put into a ſafe harbour.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that concernes <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> more then to gaine the hearts, and keepe the prayers of theſe <hi>beloved ones,</hi> and they muſt be faithfull to God that ſhall expect it; for God and his Saints are in a League <hi>offenſive</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Simulatque faedus cum Romanis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſeris; noli expectare ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um de me ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniatorem, ſed ſtatim ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti hoſti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli Romani cavendum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Polyb. hiſt. l. 3.</note> and the Saints are ready to ſay to men as <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> did to King <hi>Antiochus,</hi> while he continued an enemy to the Romans, ſo long he ſhould be ſure of him as a friend; but if once he made a League with them, he ſhould immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately looke upon him as his enemy; ſo doe the Saints ſay, while faithfull to God; they are firme to you; but if you be falſe to God, it will not be long ere you will be <hi>caſt out</hi> of the <hi>hearts</hi> of his people alſo.</p>
            <p>And that you may cleave cloſe to the people of God, there is a great deale of <hi>courage</hi> required in theſe <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> and <hi>doubtfull</hi> times; in which <hi>mercies</hi> are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>injuries,</hi> and to give thankes for them is ſet upon men as a <hi>brand of cruelty and infamy,</hi> when ſo many forſake their firſt <hi>Principles,</hi> and labour to <hi>build</hi> againe that which hitherto they have <hi>deſtroyed.</hi> At this time I ſay, men have neede of <hi>courage,</hi> or elſe they will <hi>feare and faint, and fly</hi> when danger preſents it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Truely <hi>duty</hi> is better then <hi>ſafety,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering</hi> is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:161909:3"/>then <hi>ſinning</hi> or <hi>ſhifting;</hi> crooked wayes will never bring a man to right ends; there is too much of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in them; <hi>a lying tongue is but for a moment,
<note place="margin">Perde te, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pereas. Salv.</note> and he that will ſave his life ſhall loſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Satan hath an eſpeciall <hi>deſigne</hi> upon men of <hi>eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and authority</hi> in ſuch times as theſe, that he may carry them in <hi>Tryumph,</hi> and act by them to the corrupting of many. As the Romanes having an evill eye upon <hi>Ptolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> King of Egypt for his wealth, which they reſolved to ſeize upon, but knew not how to pick an occaſion, he being in League with them; therefore they appoynted <hi>Cato</hi> a man in high eſteeme for juſtice and uprightneſſe, as <hi>Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Praedo, ut ſumma turpitudo facti authoritate tanti viri aliquantulum tegeretur,</hi> by the name of the man to collour over the baſeneſſe of the act; ſo Satans great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of late hath beene upon the <hi>Stars</hi> in our Horizon, and wee may with feare remember how many are fallen.</p>
            <p>Engage yee therefore with and for the Saints, and let the preſent dangers raiſe your reſolutions: a great minde doth riſe by difficulties, and true courage is heightned by oppoſitions. Let the birelings fly, let meteours fall, and thoſe that have cleaved to the Church of God by flattery be detected; yet is the <hi>righteous an everlaſting foundation.</hi> Let the bleſsing of Ioſeph be on your heads whom God hath ſeperated from your brethren: <hi>let your bow abide in ſtrength, and the armes of your hands be made ſtrong by the hands of the mighty God of Jacob,</hi> which ſhall be the conſtant and dayly prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Servant in the Goſpel,</hi> William Strong.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:161909:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161909:4"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached in Pauls Church <hi>London,</hi> before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and Aldermen, the 17. of May 1648.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being the day of publique Thanſgiving for a Victory obtayned by the Forces under the Command of Col. <hi>Horton,</hi> at St. <hi>Faggons</hi> neer <hi>Cardiffe</hi> in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IUDGES Chap. 5. verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So let all thine enemies periſh, ô Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. Reſp. ad Orthod q. 71. &amp; in dial. cum Tryph. p. 307. Neceſſe eſt ut in fine ſexti milleſimi anni malicia omnis aboleatur è terra, &amp; regnet per mille an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos juſtitia, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; requies à laboribus quos mundus jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu perpeſſus eſt. de divin. imperio l. 7. c. 14. Aug. de civit. Dei, l. 20. c. 7. Rev. 10.2.3.4. Pedem ponere eſt poſſeſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſibi &amp; dominium vindicare. Par. Dan. 7. c. 27.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE condition of the Church in this world, is twofold, Militant and Triumphant. The warfare of the Church, according to the Divinity of the Ancients, is to laſt till towards the end of the firſt 6000. yeares of the World, as Juſtine Martyr, and after him Lactantius, and others have obſerved. And then ſhal be another condition of the Church, which ſhall be even in this life, &amp; compared with the former, may wel be ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Triumphant and glorious. When Chriſt, that great and mighty Angell ſhall come downe from Heaven <hi>clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with a Cloud, and a Rainbow upon his head, and ſhall ſet his right foot upon the Sea, and his left foot upon the Earth,</hi> and thereby take to himſelfe the dominion of both, Revel. 10.5.6. which is called <hi>taking to himſelfe his great power and reigning,</hi> Revel. 11.17. when hee ſhall give the <hi>kingdome and dominion under the whole heaven,</hi> which was before in the enemies hand <hi>unto the Saints of the moſt High, and they ſhall poſſeſſe it for ever and ever.</hi> When their enemies ſhall bow down before
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161909:5"/>them, and licke the duſt under their feet.</p>
            <p>In this militant condition hath the Church of God beene ever ſince the fall, and how long it ſhall ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, no man can certainly determine. But it is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current judgement of our Divines, that it drawes neere an end. While this eſtate of the Church laſts, their condition will be like that, deſcribed by the Prophet, <hi>A day wherein the light ſhall neither be cleare nor darke,</hi> Zach. 14.6. full of uncertainties, and ſubject to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall changes and viciſſitudes, not ſo light that they ſhal ſay there is an end of our feares, nor ſo darke that they ſhall ſay there is an end of our hopes. Sometimes they may be under the power of the Enemy, as <hi>priſoners in a pit wherein there is no water;</hi> and by and by God will rayſe up a deliverer for them that ſhall proclaime their liberty, and be as a <hi>covering Cherub</hi> to the Ark of God, for their defence. A reſemblance of this condition of the Church, we have in the Jewiſh State, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is made the prototype of all the Gentile Churches thorowout the whole Book of the Revelation, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of the laſt times.</p>
            <p>An embleme whereof you have in the former Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pters. Firſt, the children of Iſrael did evill in the ſight of the Lord, and he gave them into the hand <hi>of Cuſhan Riſhathaim the king of Meſopotamia,</hi> and hee ruled over them <hi>eight yeeres.</hi> Then the Lord rayſed up a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to them, <hi>Oihoniel the ſonne of Kenaz Calebs yonger brother,</hi> and the Land had reſt <hi>forty yeeres.</hi> Then the chilren of Iſrael did evill againe in the ſight of the Lord and he <hi>ſtrengthned againſt them Eglon the king of Moab:</hi> and they ſerved him <hi>eighteene yeeres,</hi> and then the Lord rayſed up a deliverer for them, <hi>Ehud the ſonne of Gera,</hi> and the Land had reſt <hi>fowreſcore yeeres.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they were oppreſſed by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161909:5"/>Lord delivered them by <hi>Shamgar the ſonne of Anath.</hi> And they did evill againe in the ſight of the Lord, and he ſold them into the hand of <hi>Iabin king of Canaan,</hi> the moſt potent of all theſe enemies; for he had nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Chariots of iron, and twenty yeeres hee <hi>mightily oppreſſed Iſrael.</hi> And then the Lord rayſed for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance <hi>Deborah the wife of</hi> Lapidoth, and <hi>Barach the ſon of</hi> Abinoham, and gave the enemy into their hands. Thus God never leaves his people in affliction, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides Saviours aſwell as Perſecutors, not onely hornes, but Carpenters alſo to beat them to pieces, Zach. 1.21. A ſong of thankſgiving for this laſt victory and deliverance, is the contents of this Chapter. In which, by way of context, wee may obſerve theſe ſix particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, all which will helpe us in the duty of the preſent day.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, the heart that ſhalbe thankfull for a mercy muſt <hi>be gracious:</hi> the ſong muſt be ſung by a Deborah and a Barak, they muſt have <hi>golden vials,</hi> hearts refined and not droſſie, that ſhall have the <hi>harpes of God in their hands,</hi> Revel. 5.8. And they that ſhall ſing the Lords ſong, <hi>muſt be redeemed from the Earth, being the firſt fruits to God and to the Lambe, in whoſe mouth is found no guile,</hi> Revel. 14.4.5. An earthy ſpirit may put a man upon a prayer, his owne neceſſity will therein carry him on, to howle upon his bed for his corne, and wine, and oyle, but it is a heart only <hi>redeemed from the earth,</hi> that will enable a man to returne prayſe; ſo that if there bee ten cleanſed, we may ſay with our Saviour, Where are the nine?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, whoſoever ſhalbe thankful for a mercy muſt prize it and rejoyce in it. <hi>Gaudentis eſt gratias age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 3.1.</note> Peace offrings are called in the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Retributions,</hi> and they that thinke they have received
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161909:6"/>little, will make little conſcience of returning. There is an evill generation among the ſonnes of men, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue mercies and deſpiſe them, ſaying, Would God we had <hi>died in Egypt:</hi> Canaan is a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that eats up his inhabitants. Theſe men are ſo far from <hi>accepting the puniſhment</hi> in an affliction, that they <hi>accept not</hi> the mercy in their redemption. Mercies will diſtinguiſh men aſwell as Judgements. Some are delivered to <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,</hi> ſome to ſhame and <hi>everlaſting contempt,</hi> Dan. 12.2. O poore murmuring ſoules, to whom mercies are a burthen!</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, a thankfull heart muſt <hi>ſtir up it ſelfe</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to prayſe. <hi>Awake Deborah, awake, awake utter a ſong, ariſe Barak and let captivity captive,
<note place="margin">Eph. 5.19.</note> thou ſonne of Abino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> Thankſgiving is <hi>melody</hi> in the <hi>heart of the Lord:</hi> and before you can make melody, your Inſtrument muſt be in tune. <hi>Awake my glory, awake lute and harpe, I my ſelfe will awake right early.</hi> Yee <hi>prophane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull</hi> ſpirits <hi>(ingratus eſt qui injuriam voc at finem voluptatis)</hi> that repine at bleſſings,
<note place="margin">Sen. ad Polyb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.20.</note> and looke upon your mercies as your injuries, <hi>incredulous men,</hi> that are ſcarce willing to beleeve the things you ſee, that endeavour to bring up an evill report upon all the goodneſſe of God, <hi>procul hinc,</hi> heere is no place for you in the worke of this day. The <hi>garment of prayſe</hi> is comely, only for the upright: <hi>ye wayward ſpirits</hi> that ſlight the gift, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe your ſelves did not chuſe the meſſenger; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you like not the hand that brings it. And <hi>yee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingly compaſsionate,</hi> that ſay, ſhall we give thanks for the killing of men, and that of our owne Nation, in a Civill Warre. In this caſe the Heathen man did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare his Triumph, and therefore ſuch Thanſgivings, ſeeme not only <hi>unchriſtian,</hi> but <hi>inhumane.</hi> To ſuch I anſwer: The War, in which at firſt, ye of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161909:6"/>were eminently ingaged, and by you the Kingdom, was eyther juſt or unjuſt: if it were unjuſt, then hide your Tropheyes, and be aſhamed of your victories; for he that gives thankes to God becauſe he proſpers in a ſinne, makes God a patron thereof. But if it were juſt, you ought to rejoyce in the ſucceſſe, being the publike execution of divine juſtice, and to glorifie God in thoſe things wherein hee hath glorified himſelfe. Tis farre from us to rejoyce in the bloud of men, much leſſe of our brethren; but yet if Chriſt will ſet up his Throne upon the carkaſes of the ſlaine, heerein we may and will rejoyce.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, he that will be thankfull, muſt enlarge his thoughts by the remembrance of former mercies, and all the circumſtances of mercies preſent. So doeth Deborah, verſ. 4.5. <hi>Lord when thou wenteſt out of Seir, when thou marchedſt out of the field of Edom, the earth trembled and the heavens dropped, the clouds alſo dropped waters, the mountaines melted from before the Lord, even that Sinai from before the Lord God of Iſrael.</hi> You muſt prayſe God from the fountayne of Iſrael, and ſing both the <hi>ſong of Moſes and of the Lambe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you muſt enlarge your thoughts in all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of the preſent mercies; ſo doth Deborah, by the violence of the enemy, <hi>the kings came and ſought then fought the kings of Canaan in Tanach, by the waters of Megiddo, they tooke no gaine of money.</hi> By their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent expectations and their hopes. <hi>Why is his chariot ſo long a comming, why tarry the wheeles of his chariot? have they not ſped? have they not divided the prey to every man a damſell or two? to Siſera a prey of divers colours, a prey of divers colours of needle worke of divers colours of needle worke of both ſides, meet for the necks of them that take the ſpoyle.</hi> By the falſhood and deſertion of their friends.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161909:7"/>
               <hi>Why abodeſt thou among the ſheepfolds to heare the bleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the flocke? for the diviſions of Ruben were great thoughts of heart. Gilead abode beyond Iordan, and why did Dan remaine in ſhips? Aſhur continued on the ſea ſhore and abode in his breaches. Curſe ye Meroz, curſe ye bitterly the inhabitants thereof, becauſe they came not out to the helpe of the Lord, to the helpe of the Lord againſt the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> By the immediate hand of God in the deliverance: his arme was made bare. <hi>They fought from heaven, the ſtarres in their courſes fought againſt Siſera, the River Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhon ſwept them away, that ancient River, the River Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, a heart truly thankfull gives the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments their due honour: thoſe that God hath honoured in the worke, doe you honour alſo, and God in them. <hi>Out of Ephraim was there a root of them againſt Amalek, after Benjamin among the people, Zebulon and Nephthali were a people that jeoparded their lives unto the death, in the high places of the field Bleſſed above women ſhall Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel the wife of Heber the Kenite be, bleſſed ſhall ſhe bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove women in the Tent.</hi> It is the property of a beaſt to crop the Tree that ſhelters it, and of an unskilfull ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to diſmantle that Towne that muſt defend him. Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el was never in a worſe condition, then when all their buſineſſe was to <hi>murmur under their preſent ſufferings, and to quarrell with the Inſtruments of their deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixthly, mercies received with prayſes, muſt be followed with prayers. As prayer ſhould engage the heart to prayſe, ſo prayſes ſhould encourage the heart to prayer; and thoſe prayſes are heartleſſe and faithles, that doe not end in prayers; for when God is giving, is our fitteſt ſeaſon to be asking. So heere prayſe for a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from one enemy, drawes out the hearts in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161909:7"/>prayer againſt all Gods enemies; <hi>So let all thine enemies periſh ô Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we are come home to the Text. The particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars thereof are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The perſons prayed againſt, Gods enemies, with their note of univerſality, All thine enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the end of theſe men, Let them periſh, with that particle which, directs us to the maner, with an eminent utter and finall overthrow, So let them pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the meanes, which is by the power, the prayſes and the prayers of the Saints. Hence the points are alſo three</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>All the Churches enemies, are Gods enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly. <hi>That periſhing is their portion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>That they ſhall periſh under the power, by the prayers and prayſes of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Churches enemies Gods enemies.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label>
            </p>
            <p>It is a queſtion the Schoolmen uſually put, <hi>Num Deus poſsit odio haberi?</hi> Whether it be poſſible for the creature to be an enemy to God, who is goodneſſe it ſelfe, ſeeing evill onely is the object of hatred, which is not to be found in him? It is anſwered, That as God is <hi>bonum univerſale,</hi> hee cannot bee hated by the creature; but <hi>inparticulari,</hi> being a good, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to us, ſo men doe hate the Lord. For Men and Angels in their fall, as ſome Schoolemen obſerve, loſt three things in reſpect of God; <hi>Delectationem pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritudinis, adorationem Majeſtatis, imitationem bonitatis,</hi> They neyther delight in his beauty, nor adore his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, nor imitate his goodneſſe. Thus all men by nature are <hi>Gods enemies.</hi> But the enemies heere ſpoken of, are Iſraels enemies, enemies to God in his Church, as Pſal. 78.1. <hi>Let God ariſe, and let his enemies be ſcattered.</hi> Iſay
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161909:8"/>57.23. <hi>I know they going forth and comming in, and thy rage againſt me.</hi> Yea even all their neglects and omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards the Church, referre to God, and hee will judge them accordingly at the laſt day. <hi>I was hungry, and ye gave me no meat, inaſmuch as ye did it not to the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me.</hi> Therefore Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies heere ſpoken of are his Churches enemies.</p>
            <p>In the opening of this point there are three things to be explayned.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the Church of God in all ages and places hath met with enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>that theſe enemies are not onely theirs, but Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>ſome ſhort diſcoveries who theſe enemies are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>the Church of God hath from the beginning met with enemies.</hi> For the nature of Chriſts kingdome in this world, is to rule in <hi>the midſt of his enemies;</hi> in the world to come, he ſhall rule over them. The Apoſtle ſayth. There is a ſchema, <hi>a faſhion of the world that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth away:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31.</note> it continues not alwayes in one faſhion; but yet caſt it into what ſhape you will, and the Church of God hath alwayes found enemies in it, and uſually they have beene <hi>the greateſt perſons, and the moſt prevayling party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe enemies are of two ſorts; from without, or from within. While the Church was wandring among the Heathen, as <hi>ſheepe among wolves,</hi> what elſe could be expected? When Iſrael went downe into Aegypt, they met with a <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who by cruelty and ſubtilty ſought to deſtroy them:
<note place="margin">Pſ. 74.14.</note> and when they came into the Land of Canaan, they were as a <hi>ſpeckled bird,</hi> all the bordering Nations hated them.
<note place="margin">Jer. 12.9.</note> There aroſe fowre great Monarchies, or principall kingdoms in the world, called <hi>Beaſts,</hi> Dan. 7.1.2. chiefly for their cruelty to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161909:8"/>the Saints. Under the Chaldean Monarchy, <hi>Iſrael is as a ſcattered ſheepe;</hi> the Lions have driven him away: the former Kings of Aſſyria, Tiglath Pileſer and Salmana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer have devoured him: and Nebuchadnezzar King of Babylon hath <hi>broken his bones,</hi> Jer. 50.17. In the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Monarchy, there was an Haman and a Cambiſes, who with a Samaritan faction of their neighbours, that were neyther Heathens by profeſſion, nor Jewes by Religion, theſe rayſed a great mountaine againſt them,
<note place="margin">Zach. 4.7.</note> even the power of the whole Empire. In the Grecian Monarchy, there aroſe Antiochus, <hi>that little horne,</hi> a King of a fierce countenance, who did deſtroy wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and proſpered and practiſed againſt the <hi>holy people,</hi> waxed great even <hi>to the hoſt of heaven,</hi> and caſt downe <hi>ſome of the hoſt and of the ſtarres to the ground and ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them,</hi> Dan. 8.9.10.</p>
            <p>And in the fourth Monarchy as Pagan, there was a great red Dragon, that made warre againſt <hi>Michael and his Angels.</hi> Thus the Church of God hath alwayes met with enemies round about. But yet ſhe might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect friends within, that thoſe borne in her boſome and brought up upon her knee, that they ſhould be true and faythfull to her. But heere is the miſery, that ſhe hath alwayes found the worſt enemies to proceed out of her owne bowels. Toads, they ſay are moſt poyſonous in the wineſeller, and the tares moſt deſtructive that grow among the wheat.</p>
            <p>If an open enemy beſiege Jeruſalem,
<note place="margin">Zach. 12.2. Judah erit in obſidione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Jerom. &amp; Montan.</note> ſome of <hi>Iudah will joyne with them in the ſiege.</hi> When Jeruſalem is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Chaldeans, that bitter and haſty Nation, yet they feared more then they doe the enemy, the Rene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gado Jewes that fell off to the Chaldeans. And in their returne out of the captivity, their greateſt enemies were the Samaritans,
<note place="margin">Jer. 38.19.</note> that profeſſed <hi>to worſhip the ſame God</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:161909:9"/>with them, and would joyne with them <hi>in building a Temple</hi> to him, that by their compliance they might hinder the worke.
<note place="margin">Joſeph. antiq. l. 11. c. 8.</note> And when the Temple was built, Manaſſes the brother of Jaddaeus the high Prieſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving married a ſtrange wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. <hi>ſc.</hi> the daughter of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and being therefore by his owne brother put out of the Prieſthood, he with his father in law did by a Petition to Alexander, obtayne leave to build a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon mount Gerazim, in hope thereby to deſtroy the worſhip of God at Hieruſalem, and to draw away the hearts of the people from it. <hi>And the Church of God is never in ſo much danger, as when a S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nballet and a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſe meet in the conſpiracy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n they were ſetled in their owne land,
<note place="margin">Act. 4.11.</note> Chriſt is <hi>rejected of the builders;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 8.14.</note> he is a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence to both the houſes of Iſrael.</hi> And for the Saints,
<note place="margin">Math. 23.34.35.</note> I ſend to you <hi>Prophets and wiſe men and Scribes,</hi> and not one of theſe can <hi>periſh out of Hieruſalem:</hi> they that did profeſſe with them the ſame God, and to joyne in the ſame worſhip, ſought to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Let us now come from the Iewiſh to the Chriſtian Church, and we ſhall ſee the enmity remayne, as ſoon as the Roman Empire embraced Chriſtianity, Satan immediatly caſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a floud after the woman,</hi> the floud of <hi>Arian hereſie,</hi> and the <hi>Arian</hi> Chriſtian perſecutes the <hi>Orthodoxe,</hi> as much or more then the Pagans had done before. But this floud was ſoone <hi>dried up, the earth hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the woman</hi> againſt the Arian perſecution. Now co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es in a third ſtate of the Empire, which is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian there doth ariſe <hi>a beaſt out of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.11.</note> that hath <hi>two hornes like a Lambe.</hi> Surely now nothing is to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xpected bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> meekeneſſe and innocency; but this Lamb <hi>ſpeakes like the Dragon</hi> and the deſigne of this beaſt is to <hi>weare out the Saints of the moſt High,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note> and to make warre
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161909:9"/>upon them, and that with greater cruelty then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Arians had done before. For Rome trades in the <hi>ſoules of men:</hi> but many Nations have made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from Antichriſt, have <hi>come out of Babylon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18.13.</note> There are <hi>ten kingdomes</hi> that the Lambe will overcome, by their <hi>converſion,</hi> and they <hi>ſhall hate the whore and make her deſolate.</hi> Surely the Saints finde no enemies there: there is in the Reformed Churches <hi>a ſea of glaſſe ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with fire</hi> both of contention,
<note place="margin">Rev. 15.2.</note> and perſecution among themſelves. And they that ſlay the witneſſes dwell in the ſame ſtreet where their dead bodies he, Rev. 11.7.8. So that caſt the world into what frame and faſhion you wil, while the tearm of the Churches militant condition laſts, there will be alwayes found a prevayling party, whoſe deſigne is to <hi>weare out the Saints of the moſt High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, They that are the Churches enemies are Gods enemies, whether they bee <hi>within</hi> or <hi>without</hi> the Church. This will appeare upon theſe <hi>fowre grounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, they are Gods enemies, becauſe God and his people are in Covenant; there is a league <hi>offenſive and defenſive</hi> betweene them. You have a full expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a league, in the words of Iehoſephat, <hi>I am as thou art, my ſervants as thy ſervants, my horſes as thy horſes;</hi> that is, they ſhalbe as truely thine to uſe, as if the neceſſity were mine owne. So Gen. 12.3. the Lord Covenants with Abraham, <hi>I will bleſſe them that bleſſe thee and I will curſe them that curſe thee; I will be an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to thine enemies, and an adverſary to thy adverſaries,</hi> Exod. 23.2. And therefore they that oppoſe them are ſayd to <hi>fight againſt God.</hi> And if the people of God be worſted at any time, they can call to him as their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate. <hi>Ariſe Lord fight againſt them that fight againſt one, take hold of the ſhield and buckler, and ſtand up for my
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161909:10"/>helpe; draw out the ſpeare, and ſtop the way againſt them that perſecute me, &amp;c.</hi> 35. Pſa. 2.3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, becauſe their cauſe is Gods cauſe, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their enemies muſt needs be Gods enemies. They intitle God to it, Pſal. 74.22. <hi>Ariſe Lord, maintayne thine owne cauſe.</hi> And God by his Propht ownes it, the <hi>battell is not yours but Gods,</hi> 2. Cron. 20.12. It is for Gods ſake that all oppoſition lights upon them; <hi>for thy ſake are we killed all the day long; the reproches of them that reproched thee are fallen upon me,</hi> and they chuſe it rather then God ſhould be diſhonoured: <hi>Malo in nos murmur hominum quam in Deum:
<note place="margin">Bern. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fid.</note> bonumeſt mihi ſi Deus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnetur me uti pro clypeo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, becauſe all Gods enemies be their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and all oppoſition that is made againſt God in the wayes of his Truth or Worſhip, they take as done to themſelves; <hi>Doe not I hate them that hate thee? yea I hate them with a perfect hatred as if they were mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> As Gods friends be their friends, ſo all Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies are their enemies. And if they anſwer to their part of the Covenant, ſurely God will not faile in his.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, they are a people very deare to God, and this makes the Lord to looke upon every thing that concernes them, as being intereſſed in it. They are dear to him,
<note place="margin">Zach. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>as the apple of his owne eye.</hi> The ſonnes of his boſome, and the Father takes himſelfe concerned in all the wrong offered to his children. And as grace, though it be in it ſelfe but an accident, is dearer to God, then the ſoules of all men without it: ſo his people, though they be but few, and as an accident to the world, yet are they dearer unto God, then all the Kings and Kingdoms of the Earth beſides; they being the <hi>firſt fruits to God and to the Lambe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 43.3.4. Pſ. 105.14.</note> and therefore he gives <hi>Kingdomes</hi> for their <hi>Ranſome,</hi> and <hi>reproves Kings for their ſakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:161909:10"/>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Who are theſe enemies? We are the Church of God, even this whole Nation, therefore none of theſe are to be found amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Theſe enemies are of ſeverall ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, all prophane men that are enemies to <hi>holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> they are the Churches enemies, whoſe <hi>God is their belly, who glory in their ſhame,</hi> who are <hi>enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt.</hi> Theſe are <hi>ſpots</hi> in our feaſts, a blemiſh and a diſhonour to all our Churches. We labour at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent under a double evill of <hi>damnable doctrines:</hi> on the one ſide, and <hi>diveliſh practiſes</hi> on the other: and both theſe thinke to juſtifie themſelves, by objecting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another. The Heretique declaimes much againſt Prophanenes, and thinkes that hee hath well acquitted himſelfe; and the prophane man on the other ſide cries out hereſie, hereſie; but theſe are both enemies unto Chriſt, and to the Church of Chriſt. Prophaneneſſe hath gotten ſo much ground, there being no Magiſtrate (as it is ſayd of Laiſh) or <hi>maſter of reſtraint to put them to ſhame,</hi> that they declare their ſinnes as Sodom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>;
<note place="margin">Judg. 18.7.</note> and it is with us as Salvian in his dayes found it.
<note place="margin">De Gubern. Deid 3.</note> 
               <hi>Genus quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodo ſanctitatis eſt minús eſſe vitioſum.</hi> He is a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man that is not extreamly wicked, and he little leſſe then a Saint who is not a very Divell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Heretiques in Opinion, and Idolaters in Worſhip. They bee the enemies to the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> Revel. 11.5. men that ſpeake <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>perverſe things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 20.30.</note> turning all upſide down,
<note place="margin">Eph 4.14.</note> denying <hi>principles,</hi> overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>foundations:</hi> affirming <hi>horribilia de Deo,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.3. 2 Pet. 3.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. Polycarp. ad Philip.</note> terribilia de fide:</hi> men that uſe a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a great deale of artifice and skill to deceive: there are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>new coyned words,</hi> and <hi>canting</hi> language to corrupt the minds of the Saints, who ſet the Scripture upon the <hi>Rack</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and make it ſpeak that which the Holy Ghoſt never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161909:11"/>
               <hi>wreſting</hi> it to their owne deſtruction, and the ſubverſion of others. Such the people of God ſhould looke upon as <hi>enemies,</hi> and <hi>avoyd</hi> their communion, 2. Iohn 10. If there come <hi>any to you and bring not this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, receive him not into your houſe, nor bid him God ſpeed, for he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is pertaker of his evill deeds.</hi> If a man be once taken with an <hi>itch of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty,</hi> as to defire to heare what every man ſayth, he is neere to be ſeduced, and it is a great judgement of God to be given over to believe a lie. Vincentius Lirinenſis hath this obſervation of the ancient Saints,
<note place="margin">Adverſ. haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. cap. 9.</note> it may ſerve for our direction: <hi>Quo quis foret religioſior eo promptius novellis adinventionibus contrairet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, all thoſe that <hi>rejoice</hi> in the low <hi>conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Church of God, and deride them when they are downe, theſe the Church calls enemies. Mica. 7.8. yet ſuch there are in the Church, <hi>ſonnes of the bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> that wilbe ſcoffing, who with Haman can ſit down to drinke, when the people of God are in perplexity; men that rage and rayle, and onely expect a day when with <hi>a deſpitefull heart</hi> they may revenge themſelves, Ezek. 25.8. This was Moabs enmity they ſayd, <hi>Behold the houſe of Iudah is like unto all the Heathen:</hi> for all their boaſting of their God, they are layd waſte as other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there is no difference. Therefore thus ſayth the Lord, <hi>I will open the ſide of Moab,</hi> take away her ſtrong frontier Cities, an enemy ſhall enter into her bowels, and ſhe <hi>ſhall be no more remembred among the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, all men that reſerve themſelves, and affect a <hi>deteſtable neutrality</hi> in theſe active times, that lie at a cloſe guard till they ſee which is like to bee the ſtronger ſide, and come not forth <hi>to the helpe of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> Meroz is as truly an enemy, as Iabin the king of Canaan: for in this caſe Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Hee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161909:11"/>that is not with me is againſt me, and hee that gathers not with me ſcatters.</hi> Theſe conſult not their preſent <hi>duty,</hi> but their future <hi>ſafety,</hi> how they may ſo demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they may ingratiate with this or that party that doth prevayle. Therefore ſayle by a <hi>ſide winde</hi> and live upon <hi>futura contingentia</hi> all their dayes. To ſuch a one I ſay, thou art an <hi>enemy</hi> to the Church of God, and God is an <hi>enemy</hi> to thee.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, they that <hi>cleave</hi> to the Church of God by <hi>flattery,</hi> and proffer to build with them that they may deſtroy them: whoſe hearts are truly ſet againſt that worke of Reformation they profeſſe to further, for in their perſons they <hi>hate to be reformed.</hi> Who court the Saints of God, and ſalute them, but it is to betray them with a <hi>kiſſe,</hi> and with Ioab to ſtab them in a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement,</hi> Ezek. 29.6.7. The Lord ſayth of Aegypt, <hi>Thou haſt beene a ſtaffe of Reed to the houſe of Iſrael:</hi> they had incouraged the Iewes to rebell againſt the King of Babylon, and had promiſed to aſſiſt them; they were <hi>in promiſsione baculus,</hi> but in <hi>ſolutione arundineus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Lap. in loc.</note> and ſo became an occaſion of all the miſery that befell Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el in this deſigne. When Iſrael came out of Aegypt, there was a <hi>mixt multitude,</hi> who did cleave to them by <hi>flattery,</hi> and murmured and deſerted them when trialls came. It may be ſayd of many a man as Ruoeus of the Carbuncle, <hi>tranſlucit in modum ardentis prunae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib de Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> if you heare their words and looke upon them at a diſtance, you would thinke them to be as hot as a <hi>fiery coale,</hi> but come neere to them and obſerve their actions, and you ſhall find them to be key cold.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixthly, all Apoſtates that fall from their <hi>former principles,</hi> that now plead for that which not many yeeres, it may be not many dayes ſince, they were vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent againſt. The greateſt <hi>enemy</hi> that ever God had,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161909:12"/>was an <hi>apoſtate Angel.</hi> The greateſt <hi>enemy</hi> that ever Chriſt had, an <hi>apoſtate Church</hi> and the greateſt <hi>enemies</hi> to the Saints are <hi>Renegado profeſſors.</hi> Take heed of an Alexander, a Demas, a Julian. There was a time not long ſince, when you all ſayd, we will admit <hi>no hereſie in doctrine, no ſuper ſtition in worſhip, no tyranny in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> no man ſhall have dominion over our Lawes, or domination over our conſciences; but many have met with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an <hi>opportunity of temptation,</hi> are <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len away,</hi> and are become <hi>actors</hi> and <hi>advocates</hi> for thoſe things and perſons which before they were reſolute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and all their former deliverances are but a <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to ſhame,</hi> Dan. 12.2. The Iewes in their firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance are to meet with ſuch trouble as they had not ſince they became a Nation, which is to laſt five and forty yeeres: in which time, many that had a ſhare in the <hi>firſt deliverance,</hi> ſhall be diſcovered to be unſound, and falſe hearted, and their <hi>former deliverance</hi> ſhall bee to their <hi>eternall ſhame</hi> and diſhonour before the Saints. Surely, there are <hi>trying times</hi> coming, when no houſe will ſtand, but that which <hi>is built upon the Rocke.</hi> Its the righteous onely that is an <hi>everlaſting Foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are three obſervations which I deſire to adde to the explication, before I come to the reaſons and grounds of this emnity.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>when mens hearts are once in judgement turned to hate the Saints, the maine pleaſure of their lives comes in by their oppoſition to them,</hi> and they take very much delight in it. As Sathan not having yet his full torment, the maine pleaſure that he takes is in oppoſition againſt God, and to ſee his plots to take in a way of revenge; ſo it is with the enemies who are acted in a high degree by the ſpirit of Sathan in their oppoſition againſt the Saints.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:161909:12"/>
            <p>A mans <hi>meat and drinke</hi> in the Scripture,
<note place="margin">Fruitionem denotat &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectationem. Glaſſ. Rhetor. ſacr. p. 373.</note> is that by which the pleaſure and the comfort of his life cometh in; <hi>It is my meat to doe the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his worke,</hi> Jo. 4.34. And to note that the mayne pleaſure of the enemies lies in their oppoſition, it is ſaid to be their meat and drinke. <hi>It is their meat,</hi> Pſal. 14.4. <hi>They eat up my people as they would eat bread,</hi> they are the food that their malice feeds upon;
<note place="margin">Mos eſt in ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibus Paleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, &amp; uſque hod ie perom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Judaeam vetus conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ſervatur, ut in vicculis oppidis &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellis rotundi ponantur lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des graviſſimi ponderis, ad quos juvenes exercere ſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leant, &amp; eos pro varietate virium ſuble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare; alii ad genua, alii ad umbilicum, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii ad humeros &amp; capur non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli ſuper verticem ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis junctiſque manibus, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus extollunt.</note> and this is <hi>their drink</hi> alſo, Rev. 17.6. <hi>I ſaw the woman drunken with the bloud of the Saints, and with the bloud of the Martyrs of Ieſus.</hi> Though it prove <hi>a cup</hi> of poyſon <hi>and of trembling</hi> in the end, yet they drinke if downe as ſweet wine, Zach. 12.2. This is <hi>their recreation</hi> alſo, and that wherin they ſhew forth their ſtrength and activity; which Hierome conceives to be intended by the Holy Ghoſt, in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xpreſſion of <hi>a burdenſome ſtone,</hi> Zach. 12.3. alluding therein to the cuſtome of the Iewes, and of all thoſe Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Countreys, where in every towne and village were great round ſtones, which the yong men for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, and to ſhew forth their ſtrength, did uſe to lift <hi>pro virium varietate,</hi> ſome to their knees, ſome to the loynes, ſome to the head, &amp;c. And thus as <hi>matter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation,</hi> are the enemies lifting at the Church, every man according to his ability, and as any one dare doe more then other this way, hee accounts himſelfe the more valiant and gallant man; which made Saul in this <hi>zeale</hi> this way (which he after ſaw to be <hi>madneſſe</hi>) to go beyond his fellowes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The laſt enemies of the Church ſhall ſurely be the worſt.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſer. </seg>2</label> The fourth beaſt was divers from all the other beaſts that went before, <hi>and exceeding dreadfull, whoſe teeth were of braſſe,</hi> Dan. 7.19.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sept.</note> But upon the laſt head of the fourth beaſt there ariſe <hi>ten hornes</hi> (for the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is broken into ten Kingdomes) and <hi>after them,</hi> o <hi>behinde
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:161909:13"/>them,</hi> there doth ariſe <hi>a little horne,</hi> that ſpeakes great words againſt <hi>the moſt High,</hi> and whoſe deſign is to <hi>we are out the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dicitur de calceamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis inveteratis, Joſh. 6.13, &amp; de pannis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fritis. Jer. 38.11.</note> Dan. 7.24.25. The Originall word doth ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to weare out a thing with long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued uſe,</hi> or as a Garment is worn out by degrees, with long and conſtant wearing, ſo under this little Horne, which muſt be Antichriſt, becauſe hee riſeth with the <hi>ten hornes</hi> upon the laſt head of the fourth beaſt; and in whoſe judgement the <hi>beaſt is ſlaine, and his body deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, given to the burning flame,</hi> ver. 11.) the witneſſes propheſie in <hi>ſackcloth and aſhes</hi> 1260 dayes; in a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, mournefull and afflicted condition; that by a long and continuall oppreſſion, they may be worne out even as a garment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, the laſt acts of theſe enemies ſhall be filled with the greateſt cruelty,</hi> and with a rage that ſhall reach to heaven: Antichriſt ſhall make it his buſineſſe during all the time of his raigne <hi>to weare out</hi> the Saints, but at laſt they <hi>ſhall be killed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 11.7.8.</note> and that in the moſt inhumane ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, their <hi>dead bodies ſhall be caſt out into the ſtreet,</hi> and they ſhall rejoyce in their death, and deny them a buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: in the laſt attempts they ſhall expreſſe more cruelty and bitterneſſe,
<note place="margin">Rev. 16.16.</note> then in many hundred yeeres before. And after the reſurrection of the witneſſes, and Romes downefall, they ſhall attempt with greater violence, when <hi>the Kings of the earth and of the whole world, ſhall be gathered together to the battell Armageddon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 20.8.9.</note> And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when Gog and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gog ſhall gather <hi>the Nations toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to battell from the fowre quarters of the earth, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as the ſands of the ſea and they ſhall go upon the bredth of the earth and compaſſe the campe of the Saints round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and the beloved City.</hi> Satan ſhall have great <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> ſeeing <hi>his time is ſhort:</hi> For in the laſt dayes ſhall be the moſt glorious Reformation, the greateſt <hi>refine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:161909:13"/>ſhall paſſe upon the world by him, who ſits as a <hi>refiner,</hi> anſwerable to the degrees of <hi>reformation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.3.</note> ſuch ſhall the degrees of <hi>oppoſition</hi> be, when there ſhall be the <hi>perfecteſt reformation,</hi> there ſhall then be the <hi>higheſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> and the bittereſt perſecution.
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> In the laſt dayes the oppoſition to Godlineſſe in <hi>the power of it,</hi> ſhalbe by them that have <hi>a forme,</hi> and the <hi>perſecution</hi> of Religion ſhall in a great meaſure be under <hi>a profeſsion</hi> therof, men ſinning againſt greater light and higher workes, whoſe hearts the Divel <hi>hath touched,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Jo. 5.18.</note> and left a ſpeciall impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of divelliſhneſſe upon, and who are thereby quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for a higher way of ſinning. In the laſt dayes ſhall the great and glorious deliverances of the Churches be, when all the perſecu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing Monarchies ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the <hi>mountayne of the Lords houſe be exalted on the top of the mountaynes,</hi> that all Nations may flow to it,
<note place="margin">Zach. 14, 4. Ut Jeroſolyma non fit in um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſa valle quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum prius: ſed pateat longe &amp; latè ejus proſpectus; ita ut gentes om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eam ſcypi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant, Calv. Rev. 11, 7, 8, 9. Ezech. 37, 11.12.</note> when the Mount of <hi>Olives ſhall cleave aſunder in the midſt, towards the Eaſt and towards the Weſt:</hi> That is, whatſoever doth now overſhadow and hide the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches glory, and hinder her proſpect ſhall be removed. And God doth not uſe to afford his people great and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent deliverances, till they are deeply humbled and brought low: the <hi>ſlaying of the witneſſes,</hi> doth precede their <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and they muſt be dry bones firſt, and then the Lord ſayth, <hi>I will open your graves.</hi> Upon theſe grounds I doe conclude, <hi>that the laſt at empts of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhal be the fierceſt, and that the bittereſt afflictions and the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rpeſt perſecutions of the Church of God, are reſerved for theſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this enmity may not ſeeme ſtrange to you, the grounds of it, and all the perſecution that flows from it, are principally theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> from <hi>the contrariety and antipathy</hi> that is in their natures, there being an enmity <hi>in judgement,</hi> put
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:161909:14"/>betweene the ſeed of the woman, and the feede of the Serpent. It is part of the Divels curſe, Gen. 3.15. and it is the curſe of all thoſe that are of <hi>their father the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell.</hi> This enmity being founded in nature, muſt needs be <hi>aniverſall and indefatigable. Vniverſall</hi> for hatred carryes a man againſt all the kinde;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ariſt.</note> as grace carryes a mans love ſincerely to all the Saints, ſo this enmity foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in nature and in judgement, carryes with it a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety unto all the Saints. And though ſome ungodly men may pretend fayre, and may with <hi>their mouths ſhew much love,</hi> and this enmity may be hid, yet are they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>wolves in ſheepes clothing;</hi> and whenſoever occaſion and opportunity is offered will appear ſo to be; for that Rule will hold to the end of the world,
<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol.</note> 
               <hi>Tot hoſtes quot extranei,</hi> they that be ſtrangers to godlineſſe, are all of them enemies to it. And <hi>indefatig able</hi> it muſt needs be. A man would ſometime thinke that Satan and wicked men, having their plots ſo often defeated and brought to nought, and all the miſchiefe of them <hi>turned upon their heads,</hi> ſhould at laſt ſit down diſcouraged and give over, but they cannot doe it, becauſe it is founded in nature and judgement: and when the five ſhall ceaſe to burn, and the ſtone to move towards its centre, then ſhall their attempts and acts of hoſtility ceaſe, and never till then.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, this enmity is exceedingly acted in them by the <hi>ſpirit of the Divell,</hi> whoſe name is in regard of his oppoſition to the Saints,
<note place="margin">Rev. 9.11.</note> called <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollyon,</hi> the Deſtroyer. All ſinnes indeed are from the Divell,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.</note> and all ſinners are acted by the Divell, he <hi>rules in all the children of diſobedience:</hi> but yet ſome ſinnes are from him <hi>per modum ſervitutis,</hi> as a man ſerves Satan in them; but ſome ſinnes are from him, <hi>per modum imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> as a man reſembles Satan in them; and ſuch is this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161909:14"/>of enmity againſt the Saints, and in theſe ſins in which a man in an eſpeciall maner becomes the <hi>ſeed of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> Satan doth more directly and immediately act men then he doth in other ſinnes: and therefore Rev. 3.10. he is ſayd <hi>to caſt the Saints into priſon,</hi> it being done by his ſpeciall inſtigation and command. And therefore its noted as a ſpeciall miſery that ſhall befall the Divell after all the perſecuting Monarchies ſhall be deſtroyed, that <hi>Dragon the old Serpent the Divell and Satan,
<note place="margin">Rev. 20.2.3.</note> ſhall be bound for a thouſand yeares, and ſhut up in the bottomleſſe pit, that he may not deceive the Nations, ſc.</hi> to draw out the rage of their ſpirits in a way of perſecution as he did in times paſt, no more. And there is no ſacrifice that the Divell is ſo well pleaſed with, as he is the God of this world, as when there is offered to him the bloud of the Saints; and therefore men that are more immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruled by him, this he doth put them upon, as that with which he is chiefly delighted. Its ſayd of Julian the Apoſtate, that he had two great deſignes; one, the <hi>ſubduing of the Perſians,</hi> and the other, the <hi>rooting out of the Chriſtians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Nazian. Orat. 2. Cont. Julian.</note> and when he went in that Perſian expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in which he periſhed, he vowed if he had ſucces in that enterpriſe, he would at his returne ſacrifice to his Idols, <hi>ſc.</hi> to the <hi>Divell in them,</hi> the bloud of all the Chriſtians that were in the whole Empire; which had beene a ſacrifice with which Satan would have beene well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>And as Satan loves to ſtir up the rage and enmity of wicked men to deſtroy the ſaints, ſo he doth very much delight to make them inſtruments in their <hi>owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and that temporall as well as eternall; and hee knowes there is no ſpeedier way to deſtroy a perſon or people, then for men to rall upon <hi>the reere of the Lords hoſt.</hi> This is the ready way to take away their owne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161909:15"/>defence, and put themſelves out of the protection of God;
<note place="margin">Eſay. 49, 8.</note> for it is for the Saints ſake, and <hi>by their Covenant, that the world is continued, and the earth eſtabliſhed:</hi> it would ſoone ſinke under your feet elſe, they beare up <hi>the pillars of it;</hi> they are the rocke upon which your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ſafety is built: and had the Lord once diſpoſed of his ſonnes and daughters in their <hi>great mariage with the Lambe,</hi> he would quickly diſſolve this frame of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, and breake up the houſe keeping of the world; and Satan doth ſet men in a way of perſecution to this end that they may thereby take away their own defence.</p>
            <p>And the Divell knowes there is no ſpeedier way to ſet God in vengeance againſt a perſon or a Nation then this is, becauſe the heart of the Lord is exceeding ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der towards his holy ones, <hi>hee that toucheth them touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the apple of his eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach 2, 8.</note> which no man ſhall doe impune or unrevenged.</p>
            <p>I now come to the ſecond branch in the Text, which is <hi>the portion of theſe enemies,</hi> they ſhall periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Churches enemies ſhall aſſuredly periſh in their owne oppoſition:</hi> periſhing is their portion.</p>
            <p>For explication I ſhall lay downe theſe poſitions.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>1</label> Firſt, <hi>The deſtruction of the Churches enemies ſhall be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by their oppoſition againſt the Church,</hi> Mich. 4.11.12.13. There are many Nations gathered together againſt Zion, and their purpoſes are that ſhe may be <hi>defiled</hi> and deſtroyed; but Gods purpoſes are not ſo, <hi>they know not the thoughts of the Lord, neither underſtand they his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell:</hi> for his intention is, that they ſhould periſh in their oppoſition: <hi>aſſociate</hi> themſelves that they may be <hi>broken in peeces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 8, 9.</note> that they may be gathered together as <hi>ſheaves in a floore;</hi> that they may be <hi>threſhed</hi> by the daughter of Zion, and where they ſeeke the Churches deſtruction,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:161909:15"/>they may there be ſure to finde their owne: and in the ſame <hi>floore</hi> where they did intend to <hi>threſh</hi> the Church, there they themſelves ſhall be <hi>threſhed.</hi> Its therefore drinking <hi>a cup of poyſon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 12, 2, 3. Venemum mortiferum, appellatio for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a tremendo: Nam quaedam venena frigida ſunt.</note> So Mercer doth conceive the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſignifie, and to be no other way a cup of trembling, but from the effect of this poyſon, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome poyſons cold in ſo high a degree, that they will caſt a man into a trembling till he die; and he that drinkes poyſon hath a hand in his owne deſtruction. Its lifting at <hi>a burdenſome ſtone,</hi> and men <hi>burden themſelves with it,</hi> and are broken to pieces by their own attempts.
<note place="margin">Math. 21, 44.</note> Its <hi>falling upon a ſtone,</hi> and daſhing at it, as a ſhip againſt a rocke, and thereby ſinking it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Act. 9, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Its kicking againſt the pricks;</hi> the iron would hurt no man of it ſelfe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would the Saints, but men ruſh againſt it and are wounded thereby.
<note place="margin">Lucun.</note>
               <hi>Nec vulnus adactis debetur gladiis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſum eſt pectore ferrum.</hi> As the Lord ſayth of himſelf,
<note place="margin">Jer. 25, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Provoke me not to anger with the workes of your hands, and I will doe you no hurt:</hi> ſo he ſayth of his Church alſo, if they be kindly intreated, they are to the Nations where they live <hi>as dew from the Lord,
<note place="margin">Mich. 5, 2.</note> and as ſhowres upon the graſſe:</hi> but if men exalt themſelves againſt them, and ſeeke to <hi>caſt downe the hoſt of heaven, they become like a hearth of fire among the wood,
<note place="margin">Zach. 12, 6.</note> and like a torch of fire in a ſheafe, and they devour the people round about, on the right hand and on the left,</hi> ſo that the cauſe of their <hi>deſtruction</hi> by them is their <hi>oppoſition</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>it will be an univerſall deſtruction of all thoſe that perſicute and perſevere in their oppoſition against the Saints,</hi> whether they be enemies without or within the Church: and the great overthrowes that have beene in the world upon the enemies, have beene brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by their oppoſition againſt the holy ones. Wee may obſerve it:</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:161909:16"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>In all the enemies from without,</hi> Gen. 14. There is a famous example in one particular Saint: four kings were confederate for enlarging their dominions, and they conquered and ſubdued all the neighbouring Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, tooke the ſpoyle and carryed it away ſafely, that I may ſay as the Prophet doth of the conqueſt of the King of Babylon,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>They gathered the riches of the Nations as one gathereth egges, there was none that moved the wing or opened the mouth or peeped.</hi> They came at laſt to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, a people that for their wickedneſſe, were even <hi>humani generis opprobrium,</hi> whom God had appointed unto the greateſt judgement that wee reade of, rayning upon them <hi>brimſtone and fire (gehennam è coelo) from the Lord out of heaven:</hi> this City they tooke, plundered, carried away many priſoners, and departed. But among theſe was <hi>righteous Lot Abrahams brothers ſonne,</hi> and in taking him they dranke poyſon, and they muſt vomit him up againe, to their owne deſtruction: for God ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up the ſpirit of Abraham to purſue them, <hi>and hee gave them as the duſt to his ſword,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 41.2.</note> and as driven stubble to his bow.</hi> When Iſrael ſojourned in the Land of Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.25. Pſal. 74.14. Dan. 7.2. Jer. 50.28. Vindicta Dei activè ſumitur pro vindicta Deus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exer cebit, vindicta Templi paſſi, vè ponitur pro vindicta qua Deus ulciſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Templo ſuo illatam, Calv.</note> while they dealt well with them they proſpered for their ſakes; but when the Lord in judgement <hi>turned their heart to hate his people and deale ſubtilly with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, he brake the head of Leviathan in the waters,</hi> in the purſuit of Iſrael, and they periſh in their owne oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Afterward there were to ariſe <hi>fowre beaſts,</hi> or great Monarchies ſucceſſively in the world, and they all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh in their oppoſition againſt the Church of God: the Chaldean periſheth, but it is by <hi>the vengeance of the Temple: the inhabitants of Zion ſhall ſay, the daughter of Babylon is like a threſhing floore, its time to threſh her, for Nebuchadnezzar the King of Baabylon hath devoured me, he hath cruſht mee, hee hath made mee an empty veſſell, hee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:161909:16"/>hath ſwallowed me up like a Dragon, he hath filled his belly with my delicates, be hath caſt me out: the violence done to me and to my fleſh be upon Babylon, and my bloud upon the Inhabitants of Chaldea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Perſian Monarchy ended alſo by the ſame meanes; for the Lord of hoſts by reaſon of their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the Saints,
<note place="margin">Zach. 1.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>is jealous for Hieruſalem and for Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a great jealouſie, and is ſore d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpleaſed with theſe heathen,</hi> becauſe when he was but a <hi>little diſpleaſed they helped forward the affliction.</hi> God did intend to correct them, and the enemies intention was to deſtroy them; and for this their cruelty, wrath aroſe againſt them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hot diſpleaſure: and hence the angel from the Lord went forth to <hi>fight againſt the King of Perſia</hi> in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches quarrell,
<note place="margin">Dan. 10.20.</note> and he ſtirres up the ſpirit of <hi>the King of Grecia,</hi> and gives him a ſucceſſe in his enterpriſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Angell went out before him. Thus alſo the Grecian Empire came to an end: for in the latter times thereof <hi>when the tranſgreſſors were come to the full,</hi> and they had filled up the meaſure of their impiety, <hi>there came forth a little horne which waxed exceeding great,
<note place="margin">Dan. 8.9.11.23.24.25.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the hoſt of heaven, and caſt downe ſome of the hoſt, and of the ſtarres to the ground and ſtamped upon them:</hi> That is, as it is expounded afterwards, there ſtoode up Antiochus Epiphanes, <hi>a King of a fierce countenance, underſtanding darke ſentences,</hi> and hee did deſtroy <hi>the mighty and the holy people,</hi> the mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of his rage did break forth againſt the Saints, yea hee did ſtand <hi>up againſt the Prince of Princes,</hi> and periſhed in his owne oppoſition, <hi>for he was taken away without hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Roman Empire alſo as Pagan, muſt come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction this ſame way by their oppoſition againſt the Saints,
<note place="margin">Rev. 12 7.8.</note> for as a great <hi>Red Dragon</hi> they made warre with the Saints, fought againſt <hi>Michael and his Angels,</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:161909:17"/>prevayled not, but in their very perſecution they were deſtoyed; for it proved the ruine of all their Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, and all the Princes that did endeavour to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
            <p>The Turkiſh Empyre, now the terrour of the world,
<note place="margin">Rev. 16.12.</note> muſt be deſtroyed alſo in this very way: <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates muſt be dryed up that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt may be prepared,</hi> Dan. 11.40. <hi>At the time of the end</hi> ſc. toward the end of the Romane Empire, <hi>the King of the ſouth,</hi> the Saracen, and <hi>the King of the north,</hi> the Turk, ſhall come againſt the Romane as a <hi>whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde, and ſhall overflow, and he ſhall wax great, and ſhall ſubdue all the neighbouring nations,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall be all at his ſteps, ſc.</hi> at his devotion and at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: And towards the end of his Empire he ſhall ſet himſelfe againſt the Saints, and <hi>he ſhall plant the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of his Palace betweene the ſeas, in the glorious holy mountaine;</hi> and then <hi>he ſhall come to an end</hi> irrecoverably <hi>none ſhall helpe him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the end of the world, though in reſpect of the former perſecutions <hi>Satan ſhall be bound up,</hi> that he ſhall not ſtir up men to rage and cruelty againſt the Saints, as he had done during all the time of the foure Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,
<note place="margin">Rev. 20.7,</note> yet when the <hi>thouſand yeares</hi> of the Churches Peace and glory are expired, Satan <hi>ſhalbe loſed againe,</hi> and having but once liberty granted, he will betake himſelfe unto the ſame courſe that he had uſed in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, to ſtir up the wicked of the world in a way of perſecution of the Saints,
<note place="margin">Rev. 20.9.</note> and <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhalbe gathered together to battle, and they encompaſſe the Campe of the Saints and the beloved City, and in this their oppoſition they periſh, now <hi>fire ſhall come downe from God out of Heaven and deveure them;</hi> thus all the Churches enemies without, do periſh in their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:161909:17"/>owne oppoſition.</p>
            <p>Its true alſo of all <hi>enemies within,</hi> ſome there are that fight againſt Chriſt under his owne banner, and perſecute the Saints under the name of Saints,
<note place="margin">Cant. 5.7.</note> ſometimes <hi>the watch men that goe about the City ſmite the Church and wound her, and the keepers of the wall take away her Vaile;</hi> yet even theſe enemies, their oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will prove their deſtruction, as we may obſerve both in the Jewiſh and in the Gentile Churches.</p>
            <p>In the Church of the Jewes <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. there were a company of men roſe up againſt Moſes and Aaron 250 <hi>Princes famous in the Congregation, men of renowne,</hi> but they did it againſt their owne lives (as they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſinners againſt their own ſoules</hi>) for the Lord created a new Creation, the earth opened her mouth and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up: and when the Lord came in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to deſtroy that Church and Sate; this is the ſin that hath eſpeciall influence into their deſtruction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.34.35. <hi>Behold I ſend unto you Prophets, and wiſemen, and Scribes, and ſome of them ye ſhall kill and crucifie, and ſome of them ſhall ye ſcourge in your Synagogues, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them from City to City; that upon you may come all the righteous bloud ſhed upon the earth;</hi> therefore they that are enemies to the Saints among themſelves ſhall not eſcape.</p>
            <p>In the Gentile Churches alſo all that ever had their hearts turned againſt the Saints, it proved the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of their deſtruction. The Church of God had beene in hard travaile 300. yeares, and at laſt brought forth <hi>a man childe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12.5.</note> and he was taken up to <hi>the throne of God,</hi> that is, they obtained of God a Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: this wrought a great change in the Empire, and they became in ſhew many of them Chriſtians; but then aroſe among them a generation of perſecutors
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:161909:18"/>the <hi>floud powred out after the Woman,</hi> which had ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them up, had not the <hi>earth ſuccored the Woman,</hi> and God given her the wings of a <hi>great Eagle</hi> to flye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wilderneſſe: now the Lord will not ſuffer the perſecutor even by them that live in the Church to goe unrevenged; therefore he doth in judgment devide the Empire; <hi>the eaſterne parts</hi> he gives to the <hi>Saracens and Turks,</hi> and the <hi>weſterne part</hi> to the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalls,</hi> thoſe barbarous Nations brake in upon them as <hi>a floud</hi> and did overflow all. The <hi>Weſterne part</hi> of the Empire being broken by the Goths, there ariſe in it <hi>ten Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17.12.</note> and they contribute all their power to ſet up Antichriſt,
<note place="margin">Rev. 17.13.17.</note> they <hi>give their Kingdomes to the Beaſt</hi> to this end, <hi>and this Beaſt</hi> perſecutes the Saints more then all the former perſecutors had done, and in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution they periſh;
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.8.21.</note> for her <hi>plagues ſhall come in one day, death and mourning and famine,</hi> and ſhe ſhall be caſt into the Sea <hi>as a Milſtone,</hi> and <hi>ſhall be found no more at all:</hi> and the cauſe of all this ſhalbe that God may <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence upon them the controverſies of Zion,</hi> that he may <hi>avenge the bloud of his ſervants at her hands</hi> becauſe in her <hi>was found the bloud of the Prophets,
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.20, 24. and 19.2.</note> and of the Saints,
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.16.</note> and of all that have beene ſlaine upon the earth.</hi> And in the reformed Churches, in <hi>the ten Kingdomes,</hi> whom God will reſerve for the ruine of Antichriſt, and will uſe them in this great worke; yet there ſhall ariſe a perſecution among themſelves alſo, and in them ſhall the <hi>Witneſſes be ſlaine</hi> (for their enemies ſhall dwell in <hi>the ſame ſtreet</hi> where their deads bodies ſhall lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried) this perſecution ſhall end in their deſtruction;
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.7.8.</note> for when the witneſſes ſhall riſe from the dead, <hi>and aſcend to Heaven in a cloud their enemies beholding them,</hi> the ſame houre there ſhall be a great Earthquake, and not onely <hi>the tenth part of the City ſhall fall,</hi> but in this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:161909:18"/>Earthquake ſhall be ſlaine <hi>ſeven thouſand of theſe men;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 11.12.13.</note> there ſhall a very great deſtruction come upon the enemies to the Saints in the Reformed Churches,
<note place="margin">Reliqui ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiae prius re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes in Iſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticorum exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio &amp; calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate juſtam Dei ultionem, tribuebant gloriam Deo caeli, id eſt, ad verum creato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem converſi ſunt, Brightm. Eſay. 34.5.6.7.8. Ad conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum pro Ziona &amp; ejus cauſam vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candam, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. Annus quo rependet Deus talio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Idumaeis, qui jugiter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ati ſunt &amp; bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li gerarunt cum Iudaeis, a L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. Et quod de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumais dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt, ad uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſos Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ae hoſtes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendi certum eſt, Calv. Ad excidium Sodomae &amp; Gomorthae al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludit, in quo perpetuam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ae Dei imaginem habemus.</note> they pertaking with Rome in the ſin, ſhall be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her plagues; and the remnant ſhall be affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and converted by this deſtruction upon others, and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll give glory to the God of heaven. Thus it will be an univerſall ruine, no enemies eyther within or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, if they perſiſt in their oppoſition, ever did or ever ſhall eſcape.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>that the enemies ſhall bee ſure to meet with in their oppoſition to the people of God ſhall be an utter destruction,</hi> and exceeding fearefull; they ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in an ordinary way, nor by the common death of other ſorts of ſinners, but there is a high degree of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance prepared for them. There is a fearefull wrath comming upon Idumea, <hi>The ſword is bathed in heaven, it ſhall come downe upon Idumea, the people of my curſe to judgement, the ſword of the Lord is filled with blood, and made fat with fatnes, for the Lord hath a ſacrifice in Boz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, and a great ſlaughter in the land of Idumea; the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes ſhall come downe with them and the bullockes with the bulls, and their land ſhall be drunken with bloud, and their duſt made fat with faines.</hi> What is the ground of all this fierce wrath? its only God doth viſit upon them their cruelty to the Saints, <hi>It is the day of the Lords ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geance, and the yeere for the recompences of the controverſie of Zion: Therefore the ſtreames thereof ſhall be turned into pitch, and the duſt into brimſtone, and the land thereof ſhall become burning pitch, it ſhall not be quenched night nor day, the ſmoke thereof ſhall goe up for ever from genera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion to generation, it ſhall be waſte, none ſhall paſſe through it for ever and ever,</hi> Zach. 12.3. The Church is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to <hi>a burdenſome ſtone,</hi> which yet would be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:161909:19"/>to none and would hurt no man, if they did not <hi>burden themſelves with it;</hi> but if they will, their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>cutting they ſhall be cut in peeces.</hi> The expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Hebrew notes two things; <hi>certainty and extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: certainty,</hi> Gen. 2.17. <hi>Dying thou ſhalt die:</hi> that is, thou ſhalt ſurely die. <hi>Extremity</hi> and perfection, Gen. 22 17. <hi>In bleſsing I will bleſſe thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thy ſeed as the ſtarres of heaven, and as the ſand upon the ſea ſhore;</hi> that is, I will eminently bleſſe thee, &amp;c. It notes excellency and certainty, ſo heere to bee cut in pieces notes great deſtruction: and yet to rayſe the judgement, the Lord doth heighten the expreſſion, <hi>cutting they ſhall be cut in peeces:</hi> that is, they ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly periſh, and that not in an ordinary way, but by an eminent and utter deſtruction, Jer. 51.11. <hi>Make bright the arrowes, gather the ſhields; the Lord hath rayſed up the ſpirit of the Kings of the Medes, for his device is against Babylon to deſtroy it, becauſe it is the vengeance of the Lord, the vengeance of his Temple.</hi> And therefore is Romes ruine utter and finall; ſhe ſhallbe utterly conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire, <hi>and the light of a candle ſhall bee ſeene no more in her at all, and the voyce of the bridegroome and the bride ſhall be heard no more in her at all, becauſe in her will be found the bloud of all the Saints that have beene ſlaine upon the earth,</hi> and this bloud God doth viſit and avenge upon her.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, <hi>It ſhall be ſuch a deſtruction as all the power of the earth</hi> ſhall not bee able to prevent or reſiſt, Zac. 12.3. All that <hi>burden themſelves</hi> with the Church, ſhall be cut in peeces, though all the people of the earth be gathered againſt it. The world glory in their multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and their confederacies, as if they ſhould be able by their owne ſtrength to deliver themſelves; but the greateſt mountayne ſhall become a plaine before the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:161909:19"/>Church, not by power nor by might, but by the ſpirit of the Lord, they ſhall come to an end, and none ſhall helpe them: when Aſſyriah is in her greateſt glory,
<note place="margin">Dan. 11.45.</note> a mountayne; then muſt the worme Jacob ariſe and threſh it, and God will rayſe up <hi>ſeven ſhepheards,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich 5.5.6.</note> and <hi>eight principall men,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall diſtreſſe Nimrod in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trances thereof:</hi> a ſmall party ſhall prevayle againſt all the ſtrength of the enemy. When the Grecian Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is in its ſtrength, the Lord will then bend Judah for him, and fill the bow with Ephraim, and rayſe up <hi>the ſons of Zion againſt the ſons of Greece,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 9.13.</note> and make them as the <hi>ſword of a mighty man, and as his goodly horſe for the battell,</hi> and they ſhall be broken even <hi>without hand,</hi> Dan. 8.25. When the Turkiſh Empire ſhall bee at its height, then ſhall the River Euphrates be dryed up,
<note place="margin">Rev. 16.12.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Saints; to make way for the Kings of the Eaſt. And in that laſt and the greateſt oppoſition of Gog and Magog, where their number ſhall bee as the ſand upon the ſea ſhore, yet then their multitude and their ſtrength ſhall not preſerve them, they ſhall periſh not by the ſword of a mighty man, nor the ſword of a meane man ſhall devoure them,
<note place="margin">Rev. 29.8.9.</note> but <hi>a fire ſhall come downe from God out of heaven.</hi> There is ſurely no eſcaping for thoſe that perſevere in the oppoſition and perſecution of the Saints.</p>
            <p>I come now to the laſt Doctrine, ſo let them periſh:
<note place="margin">Apoſtrophe ad Deum inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, nos ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citat ut ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lari affectu Deum tanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum facino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum authorem ſuſprciamus, Pet. Martyr.</note> that is, as theſe have done in their oppoſition, by the prayers, by the power, and by the prayſes of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Some expreſſe it as a prayer, <hi>ſo let them periſh,</hi> by the ſame meanes, and in the ſame maner, that doe riſe up againſt the Saints. As Pſ. 83.9.10. <hi>Doe unto them as unto Siſera, as to Iabin at the brooke of Kiſon who periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Endor, they became as the dung of the earth:</hi> with ſuch a deſtruction, <hi>let all thine enemies periſh.</hi> Others
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:161909:20"/>looking upon Deborah as one that ſpake by a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Non tam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi modo, quam predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi; tempore futuro haec Hebraicè e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciantur. Qui ſic optant &amp; agunt, atque Deo bellum i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta inferre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. <hi>Doct.</hi> Dan 8.24. Eſay. 41.14.15.16. Zach. 4 6. Eſay. 59, 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat flumen anguſtum &amp; rapidum ſc. magna celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate &amp; magno impetu, &amp; ad Dominum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertur non ad hoſtem, ab Arnoldo Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. Animadv. ſacr. cap. 2. Zach. 9.13.14. and 10.3.</note> conceive it to bee a propheſie and predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the overthrow of all the Churches enemies: and they render it, <hi>ſo ſhall all thine enemies periſh,</hi> in the ſame maner, and by the ſame meanes that theſe have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Churches enemies ſhall periſh in their oppoſition, by the power, prayers and prayſes of the Saints.</hi> The branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the point are three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By their power.</hi> A weake people they uſually are if ye looke upon them in themſelves; but yet mighty through God, and terrible as an Army with banners: In the loweſt condition of the Church, and when the enemy prevayles over them, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>mighty and the holy people.</hi> When Jacob is but <hi>a worme, then hee ſhall riſe and threſh the mountaines:</hi> for God will ray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e up their ſpirits, fight their battels, gird their loynes, and ſtrengthen their hands, not by power nor by might, but by his ſpirit; and when the enemy ſhall <hi>breake in as a floud, the ſpirit of the Lord ſhall lift up a ſtandard againſt him,</hi> by rayſing the ſpirits of his people, by aſſiſting them mightily, and making them victorious againſt all oppoſition: for the Lord himſelfe doth fight againſt all the enemies, and his people are but the weapons that he doth uſe in the expedition; <hi>Iudah is his bow, and Ehraim his arrow, and his goodly horſe for the battell.</hi> And when the Lord will uſe an ungodly people as weapons in his hand, they ſhall mightily prevayle. If hee will uſe Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon as his battle axe,
<note place="margin">Jer 51.20.</note> he will <hi>with him breake in peeces the Nations, and deſtroy the Kingdoms:</hi> how much more when he will make Judah his battle axe, and his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of war,
<note place="margin">Joannes Foxe in Comment. ſuis.</note> whom he doth much more delight to uſe and honour? ſome do conceive that in reference to this victory heere by the waters of Megiddo, that laſt great battell hath its name, which ſhall bee betweene Chriſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:161909:20"/>and Antichriſt, called therefore the <hi>battell Armageddon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Brightm.</note> Rev. 16.16. which ſome render <hi>mons deliciarum,</hi> the mountayne of delights unto God and his people: and others render it <hi>mons excidii,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Par.</note> the mountayne of ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſtruction to the Churches enemies. The Churches enemies have comonly fallen by their hand in the end, Eſa. 31.8.9. The Aſſyrian ſhall fall by the ſword, not of a mighty man, and the ſword not of a meane man ſhall devoure him. Whence then ſhall his deſtruction come? Not ſo much from any inſtrument, but from the hand of God <hi>made bare</hi> therein:
<note place="margin">Ignem hanc accendi &amp; fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veri dicit in medio populi ſui, ut ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet impios non impune Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam perſequi, &amp;c. Calv. in loc.</note> and <hi>the Lords fire is in Zion and his furnace in Ieruſalem;</hi> it is out of Zion that the fire comes that conſumes the enemies, and it is into this fiery fornace they are caſt when they are deſtroyed, Ezech. 24.14. <hi>I will lay my vengeance upon Edom by the hand of my people Iſrael, and they ſhall doe in Edom according to mine anger and according to my fury, ſaith the Lord God.</hi> They that are with the Lamb, <hi>called and choſen and faithfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17, 14, &amp; 18, 6.</note> they ſhall burne Rome with fire, and <hi>reward her according as ſhe hath rewarded them, and ſhall double to her double according to her works, in the cup that ſhee filled to them, they ſhall fill unto her double.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>By their prayers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4, 13.</note> The Lord Jeſus having made the Saints together with himſelfe Heyres of the world, hee hath alſo given them a great hand in the Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the world, as they ſhall have in the Judgement of it at the laſt and great day:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6, 1, 2.</note> therefore their prayers are Decrees as wel as the prayers of the Angels, and are called by the ſame name, Iob. 22.28. Dan. 4.17.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And the great executions and tranſactions of things in the world doe paſſe through their hands;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>they binde Kings in chaynes, and Nobles with fetters of iron, this honour have all his Saints.</hi> Its obſervable that in all the great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:161909:21"/>turnings of the world, the prayers of the Saints have had the great hand.
<note place="margin">Exod. 14, 15, 16, 17. Exod. 17, 11, 12. Pſal. 76, 2.</note> Aegypt is deſtroyed in the red ſea, but it is by the prayer of Moſes. Amaleck is routed by prayer. Thereby armies diſcomfited, victories woon, <hi>in Salem God breakes the arrowes of the bow, the ſhield, the ſword, and the battell.</hi> And they that ſcape the fierceſt purſuers among men, prayer will overtake them: <hi>hee that eſcapes the ſword of Hazael and Iehu ſhall Eliſha ſlay:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King, 19, 17. Gladionon corporali ſed ſpirituali, A Lap. Ad horribilem famem ſub Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram refertur; quia Deo impe travit Eliſaeus cum ab idolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latria Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae nollent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere, Pet. Martyr. in loc. Rev. 4, 5. Rev. 6, 10.</note> and yet we know he was not a man of war, one that did handle the ſword, onely the word did goe out of his mouth and tooke effect upon them. And all the great turnings in the Chriſtian world ſince Chriſts time have beene no other then the fruit of the praiers of the Saints. The Seales in the booke of the Revelation, ſet forth the judgement of God upon Pagan Rome; and they are all in anſwer to prayers, for out of the throne <hi>ſc.</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord in the midſt of his people, <hi>proceeded lightnings and thunderings and voyces.</hi> And in anſwer to the cry of the ſoules under the Altar, who cryed with a loud voyce, <hi>How long Lord holy and true, doeſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Trumpets ſet foorth the judgements executed upon Rome Chriſtian; and theſe alſo proceede from the prayers of the Saints, for the fire caſt upon the earth in thoſe plagues was taken off the Altar,
<note place="margin">Rev. 8, 5.</note> and there were voices and thundrings and lightnings and an earthquake &amp;c. The Trumpets ſounded but it was in anſwer to prayer, after there had beene <hi>ſilence in heaven for the ſpace of halfe an howre, ſc.</hi> during the time of the incenſe offering.</p>
            <p>The Vialls ſet forth the judgements of God upon Rome Antichriſtian; and the great voice that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe Angels to powre out their Vials upon the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:161909:21"/>earth came out of the Temple: that is,
<note place="margin">Rev. 16, 1. De Templo venit quando precibus ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum aliquid impetratur, quibus man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandi partes hic tribuntur ut ſciamus quantam vim habent fideles precationes, Brightm. Rev. 11, 5, 6.</note> from the prayers of the Saints; and whoſoever ſhall obſerve the great changes in the world that all theſe ſet forth, wilbe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to acknowledge what a mighty power there is in the prayers of the Saints. And that it may appeare it was not only ſo in ancient times, he ſayth the witneſſes even in theſe latter dayes ſhall have <hi>a power to ſhut hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that it ſhall not raine, to turne waters into bloud, and to ſmite the earth with plagues as often as they will.</hi> And that this is the miſery of all the Churches enemies, <hi>If any man will hurt them, fire ſhall proceed out of their mouthes, and devour them, and who ever he be, he muſt in this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner be killed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>By their praiſes:</hi> for out of the <hi>mouthes of babes the Lord hath ordained them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8, 2.</note> that he ſhould ſtill the <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and the avenger:</hi> when <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi> and all the people promiſed God in the <hi>beauty of holineſſe,</hi> the Lord ſet <hi>ambuſhments againſt the children of Ammon, Moab,
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 20, 22, 23.</note> and Mount Sei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, which were come againſt Iudah, and they ſmote one another.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas ſung in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the earth did quake; and ſo it commonly doth at the praiſes of the Saints. <hi>The enemies of the Church doe fall before their praiſes as well as their prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now come to the <hi>Application</hi> of theſe three points for a concluſion.</p>
            <p>They ſerve for <hi>Admonition,</hi> for <hi>conſolation</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> for <hi>Admonition</hi> unto all the enemies of the Church: <hi>ceaſe your</hi> rage againſt them, your plots, your hopes; <hi>refraine</hi> from them, let them alone, they are but <hi>paſſengers</hi> and <hi>Pilgrims,</hi> they are going unto <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan;</hi> if the world be your countrey, let them quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peaceably paſſe through it, without oppoſition, or perſecution, or elſe ye will be <hi>found fighters againſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:161909:22"/>God,</hi> and ye will but meet with your owne deſtruction in the end.</p>
            <p>To enforce this Admonition, let theſe <hi>conſiderations</hi> be duely weighed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for God to give a man up to a ſpirit of emnity, and oppoſition to his people, is the greateſt <hi>ſpirituall judgement</hi> that can befall a man in this life: it is the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils curſe</hi> to be the <hi>envious man,</hi> the <hi>accuſer</hi> and the <hi>perſecutor</hi> of the brethren: and the more a mans heart is turned againſt the Saints the more fully doth this curſe take place upon him. It was the great <hi>ſpirituall judgement</hi> upon Aegypt, and a moſt dangerous fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner of their utter deſtruction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.25. It is commonly demanded by Interpreters on that place, how God is ſaid to <hi>turne the hearts of men to hate his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</hi> and it is commonly anſwered, as in the caſe of hardning <hi>Pharoahs</hi> heart: men <hi>turne</hi> their owne heerts againſt Gods people <hi>ſinfully,</hi> and God turnes them <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially, diſerved,</hi> by forſaking them, leaving them to the power of Satan, and the rage of their owne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, <hi>&amp; media diſponendo,</hi> ſo ordering and diſpoſing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and occaſions, as to draw out their rage, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice againſt his people. The greateſt ſpirituall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a <hi>hard heart,</hi> and of this <hi>hardneſſe</hi> there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall degrees; but of them all two are the higheſt, to <hi>ſit downe in the chaire of the ſcorner, and in the throne of the perſecutor.</hi> This did fill up the meaſure of <hi>Pharoahs</hi> hardneſſe, Exod. 10 28. <hi>Take heed to thy ſelfe, ſee my face no more; for in the day thou ſeeſt my face thou ſhalt dye:</hi> how would it make a mans heart tremble, to conſider how far, at this time, this judgment is powred out upon this Nation?</p>
            <p>Secondly, whatſoever any man doth in oppoſition to the Saints, he is <hi>a veſſell of diſhonour</hi> in all thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:161909:22"/>workes: it is the ſame ſervice in which the Devills are imployd, and <hi>God hates them</hi> when he doth imploy them: <hi>The Aſſyrian the rod of mine anger,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 10, 5, 12 24.</note> and the ſtaffe of mine indignation: I ſend him againſt an hypocriticall Nation, againſt the people of my wrath; and I give him a charge to take the ſpoyle, and to tread them downe like the mire of the ſtreets:</hi> and this charge of God he doth execute to the utmoſt; but was the Lord well pleaſed therewith? he ſaith <hi>when he had performed his whole worke upon Zion, the indignation ſhould ceaſe, and his anger in his deſtruction:</hi> and it's a hard ſervice to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in that which brings forth neither acceptance nor reward, but indignation and deſtruction in the end.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, your very oppoſition will prove your deſtruction; <hi>the pit that you dig</hi> for the Saints yee ſhall ſurely <hi>fall into,</hi> it is a worke that ever ended in the ruine of the Actors, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 59.5. It's ſaid of wicked men, <hi>that they hatch cockatrice egges, and they weave a ſpiders webbe, the webbe never becomes a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the egges curſed breakes into a Viper:</hi> it ſets forth two properties, and fruits of al the labours of the workers of iniquity; they are unprofitable, they attaine not their end in them, and they are <hi>deſtructive,</hi> they bring forth a Viper that ſtings him to death that hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, and the wrath of God will never be pacified, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once provoked, till it end in their utter overthrow, <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.8. when the Angels as inſtruments of vengeance went into the north Countrey <hi>ſc.</hi> into <hi>Perſia</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea;</hi> and they have quieted my ſpirit, ſaith the Lord; that is they pacified my wrath by <hi>executing</hi> vengeance upon the perſecutors, the people of my wrath: let me reaſon with you a little, was there no other way of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that could bring vengeance enough upon you, and ſinke you deepe enough into perdition but ye muſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:161909:23"/>
               <hi>touch the apple of the Lords eye.</hi> May not I ſay with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Was not the iniquity of Peor enough, from which ye are not cleanſed unto this day?</hi> Was not your drunkenneſſe, ſwearing, uncleanneſſe, hatred of godlineſſe, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, enough, but that you muſt breake forth into perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution alſo?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, your deſtruction is neereſt when yee are higheſt, when your confederacy is ſtrongeſt, and your hopes rayſed to the greateſt perfection: when the enemy is as ſmoake out of a chimney and doth threaten even to darken the Sunne, then ſhall they bee ſcattered, Hoſe 12.3. When they aſſociate themſelves, and have the greateſt combination of parties and counſels, then they ſhall be broken in pieces.
<note place="margin">Eſay. 8, 9, 10.</note> When they are folded together as thornes, and drunken with confidence as the drunkards, then ſhall they be conſumed as ſtubble fully dry. The Lord doth many times lay the Church low in a deſigne, that the enemy may put forth their power and ſhew foorth their malice to the utmoſt againſt it; therefore he is ſayd to make Ieruſalem <hi>a cup of poyſon:</hi> no man attempts to drinke wine while it is in the pipe or in the veſſell: the Church of God is alway poyſon to the enemies, but not alway put into a cup and made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and fit for their mouthes: but when the Church of God is brought into a low condition, its then prepared to invite the enemy as it were to attempt ſome thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; partly from the pleaſantneſſe of ſuch a draught, and partly from the eaſe of it, its as eaſie as to drink, and they can make no reſiſtance. The Church is ſometimes a great ſtone,
<note place="margin">Zach. 12, 2, 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> even as a mountayne, and it fils the earth; and then the enemies dare not attempt to burden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therewith, but ſometimes it is a ſtone of a leſſer ſize, and then they are ready to thinke they may carry it away with caſe; whereas though it be not alwayes ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:161909:23"/>great, yet it is as heavy, and they finde it ſo, for it <hi>breaks them to peeces.</hi> Whenſoever the Church of God is brought low it is in deſigne, that their enemies may be enſnared and taken.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fiftly, by theſe means ye ſhall bring upon your ſelves the guilt of all the bloud of the Saints that hath beene ſhed in former ages. To reade of the cruelty of Pharaoh, Nebuchadnezzar, Antiochus, the Iewes in crucifying the Lord of Life, and of the ten bloudy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, and the rage of Antichriſt ſurpaſſing all theſe; and to have all this bloud lie upon one generation, who would not tremble at it? But yet all the bloud of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times will come upon the perſecutors of this laſt age of the world. Matth. 23.34.35. <hi>That upon you may come all the righteous bloud ſhed upon the earth, from the bloud of righteous Abel, unto the bloud of Zacharias the ſon of Barachias.</hi> It is much queſtioned how this is to bee underſtood, that the bloud ſhed in one age ſhould in the guilt of it come upon another, and how the bloud of all former ages ſhould come upon this laſt?</p>
            <p>To underſtand it rightly, theſe two things are to bee conſidered.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, that it is to be underſtood only in reſpect of temporall puniſhments and not of eternall; for as no man ever went to heaven by the righteouſneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meere man, ſo no man ſhall ever goe to hell for the wickedneſſe of another. Heere the ſonne ſhall not bear the iniquity of the father, but the ſoule that ſinnes ſhall die. Yet in things temporall, as children may have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſings, as a reward of their fathers graces and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience (as God brought Iſrael into Canaan,
<note place="margin">2. Cron. 20.7.</note> although they were a very diſobedient and ſtiffenecked people, becauſe it was the Land which he had promiſed to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham his friend: and hee delivered them in the dayes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:161909:24"/>of Hezekiah for his ſervant Davids ſake) ſo they may be under many temporall judgements,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 37.35.</note> as a puniſhment of their fathers diſobedience: the Lord heerein uſing his ſoveraignty and prerogative to puniſh a man eyther in his perſon or his poſterity,
<note place="margin">Gen. 9, 25. 2 King 5, 27.</note> as he did Cham in Canaan his ſon, and Geheſie both in his perſon and in his ſeede alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, God lookes upon a generation or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of men as a body, and in the puniſhment of their ſinnes he doth ſhew both juſtice and providence. As there is a meaſure of iniquity in particular men to bee filled up before eternall wrath ſhall take hold of them,
<note place="margin">Jer. 51, 13. Dan. 8, 23. Zach. 5.6. Joel. 3, 13. Rev. 14, 15.</note> ſo is there a meaſure appointed alſo to a State, or a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of men, which muſt be filled up before Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall wrath ſhall come upon them. Wee ſee the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall judgement upon the Amorites is deferred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their <hi>iniquity was not yet full,</hi> and the time to fill it up was 400 yeeres, Gen. 15.16. The Lords Decree is gone forth to <hi>blot out the remembrance, of Amalecke from under heaven,</hi> Exod. 17.14. and yet this people doe not come up into remembrance before the Lord to their utter deſtruction till the dayes of Saul, 1 Sam. 15.2. and then the Lord ſits upon their poſterity their fathers ſinnes, <hi>becauſe they layd wayt for Iſrael in the way when they came out of Egypt.</hi> So Chriſt ſayth to the Phariſes; <hi>ye are the children of them that killed the Prophets, fill yee up the meaſure of your fathers,</hi> Matth. 23.31.32. So that when children walke on in their fathers wayes, and fill up their meaſure, though in reſpect of eternall wrath inflicted upon their perſons, they were in hell many yeeres agoe, and received a juſt recompence of reward, yet the temporal puniſhment may be reſerved for after ages, and viſited upon the poſterity when tranſgreſſion is come to the full. Thus all the cruelty executed upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:161909:24"/>the Saints from the bloud of Abel was viſited upon the Jewes in the deſtruction of Jeruſalem, and all the bloud ſhed upon the earth ſhall be viſited upon Babylon the great the mother of harlots, when ſhe ſhall come up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to remembrance before God, with all thoſe that have receyved her marke, or borne her image, or acted with her in a way of bloud.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Sixthly, there are no ſort of ſinners in whoſe deſtruction the Lord doth ſo much delight; it is unto him a ſacrifice of a ſweet ſavour, Eſa. 34.6. Jer. 46.10. Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ph. 1.7.8. And as Satan the neerer his kingdome is to end, the greater is his rage, <hi>great wrath becauſe his time is ſhort,</hi> ſo the neerer Chriſt comes to the perfect poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Kingdome (for when the enemies are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, all the Kingdomes of the earth ſhall be the Lords and his Chriſts) the more will he put on zeale as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the more he will haſten the enemies over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw: he will doe more in a ſhort time at laſt, then hee hath in many ages in times paſt. If it bee but a ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,
<note place="margin">Quid tandem Deus Opt. Max. in te de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernet? Sagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ſuas deſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; nec non carbones ſeu primas Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perorum in Gehenna. Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. in loc.</note> or one that perſecutes with a deſpitefull heart and a falſe tongue, he ſhall not loſe his labour: therefore the queſtion is put, Pſal. 121.3.4. What ſhall be given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, or what ſhalbe done unto thee thou falſ tongue? Thy reward from the Lord ſhalbe, mighty and ſharp ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes with coales of Iuniper, which as they burne hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and continue the longeſt, ſo they doe in the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yeeld a ſweet ſavour.</p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe is for conſolation to all the Saints,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> and the Lord takes great care that they ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, that their ſpirit might not ſinke and fayle in the evill day: Comfort yee, comfort yee my people,
<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.1.</note> ſayth your God: and when the Lord Chriſt drew neere his ſuffering, when a man would have expected all his thoughts ſhould have beene taken up about himſelfe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:161909:25"/>yet now he takes care to beare up the ſpirits of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that they might not bee overwhelmed with over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much ſorrow, Io. 14.1. Let not your hearts bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled &amp;c. Truly we had need of great ſupports, becauſe the enemies are many and enraged, mens ſpirits are in judgement turned to hate the Saints, and it is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if a man rightly diſcernes the ſignes of the times, that the killing of the witneſſes drawes neere, which will ſurely bee the bittereſt and bloudieſt perſecution that ever befell the Chriſtian Churches.</p>
            <p>My purpoſe is not to give you thoſe ordinary ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports which are common to all afflictions, as that they come from a fathers hand, from a heart full of love, that they ſhalbe in meaſure, and make a man partaker of the holineſſe of God in the end, for this is all the fruit to take away the ſinne &amp;c. though theſe are great grounds to ſtay a mans faith upon. But I would rather pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe that might be more proper and peculiar to the enemies and ſufferings of the laſt times, the cup that God hath reſerved for you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe ſhalbe the laſt great ſuffrings of the ſaints, and they ſhalbe but ſhort; for as all the former beaſts are deſtroyed, ſo there now remaines onely the ſeventh head of the fourth beaſt, which is as the eight and muſt goe into perdition, Rev. 17.11. and then all the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent perſecutions of the Church ſhall ceaſe, and there ſhall be no more a pricking briar, and a grieving thorne in the Lords holy Mountaine: the Lord ſhall then wipe away all teares from your eyes, there ſhall bee no more ſorrow, nor crying, the witneſſes ſhall die but once, and it ſhalbe the ſharpeſt but yet the ſhorteſt of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſufferings. To all you that have beene with the <hi>Lambe called and choſen and faythfull,</hi> I ſay as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr did, Hold out faith and patience, your worke is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:161909:25"/>at an end. It was a great comfort to Hierome of Prague, that he could ſay to his perſecutors at his death, <hi>Centum revolutis annis Deo reſpondebitis &amp; mihi:</hi> after an hundred yeeres God would call them to an account in avenging his bloud; but you may ſummon your perſecutors before God to anſwer in a far leſſe time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, theſe laſt ſufferings ſhall be an inlet to the moſt glorious deliverances that ever the Church of God had: for the killing of the witneſſes ſhall make way for their reſurrection,
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.12.15.</note> when they ſhall <hi>aſcend to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in a cloud, their enemies beholding them.</hi> And then ſhall the Kingdomes of the earth become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Lord, and the dominion under the whole heaven ſhall be given to the Saynts of the moſt High,
<note place="margin">Dan 7.27.</note> and they ſhall poſſeſſe it for ever and ever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, all your ſinfulneſſe and unworthines, ſhall not hinder your redemption: though the people of God fall, yet they ſhall riſe, and though they may ſit in darkneſſe, the Lord will bee light about them. Indeed the great diſcouragements to the Saints are their ſinnes, and their unanſwerable walking unto meanes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but yet the Lord cannot alter the word gone out of his lips, nor ſuffer his faythfulneſſe to fayle, Eſay 10.27. <hi>The burden ſhall bee taken away from off thy ſhoulder, and the yoke from off thy necke, and the yoke ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, becauſe of the annointing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Glaſſ. Rhetor ſacr. Calv. in loc.</note> Some take the annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for Chriſt the annointed of the Lord, and others for the Kingdome of Chriſt, which by an unction the Lord had eſtabliſhed, whether Chriſt or the Kingdom of Chriſt be underſtood, yet there is an annointing that will breake every yoke. Their ſinnes may procure their affliction, but they ſhall never hinder their redemption.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, The enemies ſhall never bee able to ſet up Popery in this kingdome againe, and to eſtabliſh
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:161909:26"/>any of thoſe things that relate to it; that the Lord hath removed in theſe late yeeres, they ſhall never bee able to root out the Saints out of the Reformed Churches, but they ſhall grow by their oppoſition. Chriſt will ſurely keepe the ground that hee hath won in a way of Reformation; and what the former vialls have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall never be made up againe, for hee will not loſe the fruit of his conqueſt in any one of them. His ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of heaven and earth are to this end, that hee may remove the things that are ſhaken as of things that are made, that thoſe things that cannot <hi>be ſhaken may remain</hi> Heb. 12.27. There is nothing that is made by man in the things concerning God, but he will have a ſhaking time for it, and his end in ſhaking it is, that hee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move it, and he doth not ſo remove it, that the enemies ſhould againe eſtabliſh it. And therefore what ever of Popery the Lord hath ſhaken and removed, I doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that all the power of the enemy ſhall never ſet up againe. I doe not doubt but there will bee many and deſperate attempts for it, but they ſhall never bee able to prevayle, as when the Heatheniſh way of worſhip was deſtroyed, there were many endeavoured to ſet it up againe.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>God will in an eſpeciall manner owne you in all your ſufferings,</hi> as he calls you forth for him, ſo will hee aſſuredly appeare for you; and therefore he ſaith when men reject them and caſt them out,
<note place="margin">Rev. 11.3.</note> they are <hi>my two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> and they ſhall have the ſame power with him that any of the <hi>ancient Saints</hi> have had in times paſt, they ſhall <hi>turne water into bloud</hi> with Moſes and Aaron, they ſhall <hi>ſhut Heaven that it ſhall not raine,</hi> with Elijah, they ſhall be <hi>two Olive trees ſtanding before the God of the earth:</hi> with Joſhua and Zorobabel, if any man hurt them <hi>fire ſhall come out of their mouthes and devour them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:161909:26"/>and they ſhall ſmite the earth with plagues as often as they will;</hi> ſo that the greater perſecution they ſhall meet with all from men the nearer <hi>acceſſe</hi> they ſhall have to God and the greater <hi>acceptance</hi> with him, and as the <hi>affliction</hi> ſhall abound, ſo ſhall alſo the <hi>conſolation,</hi> and to be owned eminently by God, and to be looked upon as thoſe of whom the world is not worthy, when they are diſowned by men and accounted not worthy to live in the world, is a great meanes to beare up mens ſpirits in the greateſt ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, <hi>It ſhall end in their finall and utter deſtruction;</hi> for there ſhall follow an <hi>earthquake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 11.13.</note> in which <hi>the tenth part of the City ſhall fall:</hi> Chriſt ſhall be clothed with <hi>a veſture dipt in bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19.13.15.</note> and he ſhall tread the wine preſſe and fierceneſſe of the wrath of Almighty God, and all thoſe ancient Propheſies, as well for the enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction as for the Saints redemption ſhalbe fullfilled; for time or delay ſhalbe no more,
<note place="margin">Rev. 10.6.7.</note> the myſtery of God ſhalbe finiſhed, as he hath declared to his ſervants the Prophets; and then ſhall that ancient prediction of Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius be fullfilled,
<note place="margin">De divino praemio lib. 7. c. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Romanum nomen quo nunc regitur ab orbis (horret animus dicere, ſedd cam quia futurum est,) tolletur de terra.</hi> All that power of <hi>Rome</hi> which hath for many hundred yeares, as the fourth Beaſt ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over the Churches, all this ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the little horne,
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.11.26.</note> and the Beaſt given to the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning flame, to be conſumed and deſtroyed unto the end.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially by <hi>Iulian,</hi> who did in diſpight to Chriſt and Chriſtianity uſe all meanes to bring in <hi>Pagan Idolatry</hi> againe, and to build the Temple at Jeruſalem, and to ſet up againe the Jewiſh worſhip; and to this end ſet a great multitude of poore deluded Jewes about this worke; but when they had gotten materialls to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:161909:27"/>and thought to ſet about the building: that night the Lord ſent a whirl-winde, and ſcatered all the materialls; but they were not thus diſcouraged from the worke, but they ſought out the ancient foundation of the Temple to build upon it, and having found it, the Lord ſent an earthquake, which caſt up all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer foundation; and then that Propheſie was full filled, there was not a <hi>ſtone left upon a ſtone not throwne downe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecce globus igneus e fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentis Templi erum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peus laboran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus occur tens, operari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os multos am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſit, incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o illo per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diem du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante. Ea mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racula quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Iudaeos ita permove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ut Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Deum agnoſcerent. Religio vero indurati cum indignatione opus caeptum dereliquerunt. Oſiander Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. Cent. 4 l. 3. c. 34.</note> but ſuch was their blindeneſſe and deſperate madneſſe, that they would not deſiſt from the enterpriſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord ſent a fire out of the foundations of the Temple, which conſumed many of the workmen, their materialls and inſtruments for the building, and then at laſt they began with ſhame and indignation to give it over. The like endeavours wee may expect for Rome Antichriſtian, and with greater violence, but they ſhall be alway ſo croſſed that they ſhall at laſt periſh in their owne oppoſition: what ground the Lord hath won up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Rome he will maintayne, for he will by degrees de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy her.</p>
            <p>Neyther ſhall they ever prevayle to root out godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or a godly party out of this Kingdome, but they ſhall encreaſe by perſecution raiſed againſt them: for as the ten Kingdomes did at firſt give their power to the Beaſt to ſet him up, ſo he will turne their hearts to hate the whore, and they ſhall plucke her downe, for the Lambe ſhall overcome the ten kingdomes, not in a way of deſtruction but in a way of converſion, and hee will win ground upon them dayly, and will have a prevay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling party in them, who ſhall bee the more ſtirred up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her for her laſt cruelty, <hi>and they ſhall hate her, eat her fleſh and burne her with fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>laſt uſe</hi> is for direction to thoſe that feare the Lord;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> and that in three particulars, and I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:161909:27"/>
            <p>Firſt, let this preſent mercy raiſe your hopes, and revive your now drooping and ſinking ſpirits: truly had you no pledge given,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tum cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ejus Montan.</note> yet there is ground enough of encouragement in the Lord, Pſ. 112.7.8. <hi>Truſting in the Lord his heart is eſtabliſhed:</hi> the word ſignifies under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped, which of it ſelfe would fall and ſincke. But much more when God gives in mercy for an earneſt,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.4.</note> experience ſhould bring forth hope. This ſhewes that God hath not yet ſold us into the hands of our enemies, that he will yet goe forth with our armies: let this bee added to the former manifold experiments that you have had, and let it be as the head of Leviathan,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> food for your fayth to feed upon in the wilderneſſe, which as yet ye are to paſſe through before ye enter into reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, though your power bee ſmall and your party few and weake, that by power you have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hope to prevable, yet by the meanes you have, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and prayſes, and by them God hath ordayned that ye ſhall <hi>ſtill the enemy and the avenger:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.2. Rev. 11.5.</note> the fire with which they muſt bee killed, muſt proceed out of your mouths. Flie to the old refuge of faſting and prayer in a communion of Saints, formerly practiſed when perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, but now wholly neglected, when it may with li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty be enjoyed: truely in theſe your ſtrength lyes; and prayer never comes too late. In the time of <hi>Eliah</hi> when it rained not upon the earth in three yeares and fix moneths, one would have thought now the rootes of all hearbes and trees were withered in the grownd, and prayer now could do little good; but <hi>Eliah</hi> prays, and God ſends raine, and the earth yeeld; her fruit as in times paſt. <hi>Prayer in the moſt deſperate ſtate of things comes not too late, becauſe God can never come too late.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, that you may unite your prayers, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to unite your hearts, and if you deſire that God
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:161909:28"/>ſhould ſhew himſelfe againſt your enemies,
<note place="margin">Prima iratum tela ſunt male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicta &amp; quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus imbc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilli optamus irati. Salv. de gub. l. 3. Dr. Reynoldes ſelfe-denyall.</note> be not ye enemies one to another, let all jealouſies, evill ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, all bitterneſſe, ſlanders, and reproaches be layd aſide as becomes perſons profeſſing Godlineſſe, ſpeake not evill one of another the judge ſtands before the doore. It is well obſerved by a learned Divine of our owne, that the former diviſion of Conformiſts and non-Conformiſts in this Kingdome was cheriſhed, and fomented by an Epiſcopall intereſt, that they might ſpend themſelves one againſt another,
<note place="margin">Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. 37.19. Rev. 22.1. Homines do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti &amp; Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Miniſtri pace ingrati ac buſi ſunt ac multas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiones &amp; rix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſimplici doctrinae im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuerunt ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mutuo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedi gladian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſimplicem populum ab u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ae in varias ſectas adduxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Caſtigavit igitur Deus Eccleſiam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am propter contentiones, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ixas &amp; ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta non tantum Ariana perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutione ſed &amp; nova ethnica. &amp;c. Bulling. de perſecutioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Eccleſ. Chriſtian.</note> and the other might have objects for their favours and their frownes to worke upon in them both. Some ſuch principle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently workes in our preſent diviſions, that both parties ſpending their ſtrength, and being ſo zealouſly buſied one againſt another. A third party being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected (if I may not ſay courted) by both, may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, and inſenſibly grow up, and come in to deſide the controverſie, which I aſſure my ſelfe they at this day confidently expect; there is a glorious union promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be betwene the people of God in the latter daies, the long breach betweene the ten and two Tribes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jewes ſhalbe made up, and the two <hi>ſticks</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came one in the Prophets hand, and the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that is in the Sea of glaſſe in the reformed Churches ſhall be put out, and ſhall againe become cleere as Chriſtall; but it will be ſome great affliction that muſt make up this u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, being melted they will ſoder, but not elſe. It is obſerved that after the reformation in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time there aroſe great diviſions, and contentions amongſt themſelves, eſpecially in the Miniſtry, and therefore God gave them up in <hi>Iulians</hi> time, into the hand of the Heathen; ſo <hi>Rome Pagan</hi> had for three yeeres and halfe a reviving: ſo ſhall <hi>Rome Antichriſtian</hi> have three years and halfe, and the growned of it I feare will be our own
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:161909:28"/>diviſions alſo. This Parents uſe to doe if children can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree among themſelves; they whip them both. And every man knowes that no man gaines by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between brethren, but he that is an enemy to both.</p>
            <p>I thinke every one that is wiſe hearted, doth more feare our owne diviſions then all the enemies combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for what is ſayd of England, may be as truely ſayd of thoſe that feare God in it. <hi>It is a mighty creature that can never dye unleſſe it kill it ſelfe.</hi> My humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is that of <hi>Nazian.</hi> to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that you would uſe all your Authority and intereſt to put an end to the differences between theſe that are godly, and act upon conſcientious principles.</p>
            <p>Our differences are not ſo great,
<note place="margin">Nos quantum in nobis eſt, propter haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos cum col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legis &amp; coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis noſtris non contendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; cum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus divinam concordiam &amp; dominicam pacem tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: Servatur a nobis pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter &amp; fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter collegii honor, vincu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum fidei &amp; concordia Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotii, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. ad Juba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian. Epiſt. 73. Zach. 12.3.</note> that wee ſtand at ſuch a diſtance, that to hold an opinion a man ſhould hazard his deſtruction. In <hi>Cyprians</hi> time they could keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace, with thoſe that did not onely thinke, but teach that which was contrary to what was received, in things of leſſer concernment: and ſurely wee might in our differences at leaſt ſo far agree as to act together, if pride and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were layd aſide, and wee acted by the ſame ſpirit of humility and brotherly love, that the ancient Saints and Churches were.</p>
            <p>And if this deſigne of union might take place, though the enemy threaten and the clouds gather and grow black every day more and more; yet I ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe that all that burthen themſelves with the Saints, ſhould <hi>be cut in pieces,</hi> though all the <hi>people of the earth ſhould be gathered together againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
